<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The birth of a day: being a treatise theologicall, morall and historicall, representing (as in a scene) the vicissitudes of all humane things, with their severall causes and sacred uses. Compos'd for the establishing mans soul unchangeable in the faith, amidst the various changes of the world. / By J. Robinson Mr of Arts and preacher of Gods Word.</title>
            <author>Robinson, John, Preacher at East-Thorpe.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 159 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91893</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1698</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1493_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203378</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863348</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863348</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115543</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91893)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115543)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 191:E1493[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The birth of a day: being a treatise theologicall, morall and historicall, representing (as in a scene) the vicissitudes of all humane things, with their severall causes and sacred uses. Compos'd for the establishing mans soul unchangeable in the faith, amidst the various changes of the world. / By J. Robinson Mr of Arts and preacher of Gods Word.</title>
                  <author>Robinson, John, Preacher at East-Thorpe.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 102, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Roger Daniel; and are to be sold by Thomas Johnson, at the sign of the Golden Key in S. Pauls Churchyard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655. [i.e. 1654]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nouemb: 17"; the second 5 in the imprint date has been crossed out and replaced with a "4".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115543:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE BIRTH OF A DAY: BEING <hi>A Treatiſe Theologicall, Morall and Hiſtoricall,</hi> Repreſenting (as in a Scene) the Viciſſitudes of all Humane things, with their ſeverall Cauſes and ſacred Uſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Compos'd for the establiſhing mans Soul unchangea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the Faith, amidst the various Changes of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By J. ROBINSON Mr of Arts and Preacher of Gods Word.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Iſa. 21. 11, 12.</bibl> 
               <hi>He calls to me out of</hi> Seir, <hi>Watchman, what of the night? The watchman ſaid, The morning cometh and alſo the night.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Roger Daniel;</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Thomas Johnſon,</hi> at the ſign of the Golden Key in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Churchyard, 1655</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:115543:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115543:2"/>
            <head>To the RIGHT WORSHIPFULL S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>G. B. Knight.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the wheeling motions of our late</hi> changes <hi>I have ſtill obſerv'd you to be</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo quadratus, <hi>one whoſe</hi> Baſis <hi>hath been firmly grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> Religious principles; <hi>and amidſt the manifold Alterations of the World's Scene (on which you have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the</hi> ſuffering <hi>part) moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant unto the</hi> Truth; <hi>your Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Soul over-looking theſe ſubluna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:115543:3"/>
mutations with an eye of</hi> Faith <hi>fixt upon</hi> Eternity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Having therefore compos'd this Treatiſe,</hi> [The birth of a Day] <hi>brought forth by the midwifery of ſome weeks ſtudies, I no ſooner thought of ſeeking a</hi> Patron <hi>for it, then of chooſing</hi> Your ſelf; <hi>whoſe</hi> Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence <hi>(I knew well) could fully at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt the</hi> Viciſsitudes <hi>of all</hi> Humane things, <hi>and whoſe</hi> Judgement <hi>did clearly diſcern their ſeverall</hi> Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>as having already apply'd them home in their</hi> ſacred Uſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the rather, S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, do I make bold here to inſcribe</hi> Your name, <hi>that I may erect, if but a</hi> ſmall Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:115543:3"/>
               <hi>of</hi> Thankfulneſſe <hi>unto you for ſundry</hi> Favours; <hi>and let you ſee that I eye not</hi> Greatneſſe <hi>ſo much as</hi> Goodneſſe <hi>for the fitteſt</hi> Patron. <hi>The former of theſe having much of</hi> Viciſsitude <hi>in it, being</hi> Aurâ fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacior, <hi>more fleeting then the</hi> Air; <hi>but the later of duration, being</hi> Aere perennior, <hi>more durable then</hi> Braſs. <hi>And a greater teſtimony of this</hi> Goodneſſe <hi>cannot be given, then your eminent and cheerfull</hi> ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>even the loſſe of</hi> All, <hi>your</hi> Conſtancy <hi>excepted in the</hi> Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Faith, <hi>which hath taught you to look beyond the</hi> Inſtruments, <hi>unto</hi> God <hi>the</hi> principall Agent, <hi>in his ſo
<pb facs="tcp:115543:4"/>
various and changeable dealings with you, as to earthly things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>May theſe Lines then stand you in any ſtead, though to be only (as</hi> Aaron <hi>and</hi> Hur <hi>were to</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes) <hi>ſome ſtay and ſupport to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exod. 17. 12.</note> 
               <hi>your</hi> weak hands <hi>and</hi> feeble knees, <hi>it is enough.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For God who is rich in</hi> mercy <hi>to thoſe that call upon him, hath a</hi> Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficit <hi>for</hi> You <hi>and</hi> Yours, <hi>and will at length make up all your</hi> loſſes <hi>(if you</hi> faint <hi>not under them) out of his own choiceſt</hi> treaſure <hi>of</hi> happineſſe, <hi>which no</hi> ſon of violence <hi>ſhall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to force from You; ſince you have ſuffer'd as a</hi> Chriſtian <hi>with undaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:115543:4"/>
Fortitude <hi>and</hi> Patience, <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in your ſelf that you have in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a</hi> better <hi>and an</hi> enduring Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And now, Sir, I commend your</hi> VVorthy ſelf <hi>with your</hi> Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous <note place="margin">Act. 20. 32.</note> Lady, <hi>and your</hi> hopefull <hi>(as well as</hi> numerous) branch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, <hi>unto</hi> God <hi>and the word of his</hi> Grace: <hi>nothing doubting but that He, who by the hand of his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence hath the</hi> turning <hi>about of this great</hi> Globe <hi>of the</hi> World, <hi>will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in his good time,</hi> turn <hi>all to his</hi> Churches good: <hi>and as he is</hi> able <hi>every day to build you up more and more in your</hi> Holy Faith; <hi>ſo
<pb facs="tcp:115543:5"/>
likewiſe he</hi> will <hi>do it, and give You an</hi> abiding inheritance <hi>among them that are</hi> ſanctified. <hi>Which is the</hi> prayer <hi>of him who eſteems it an</hi> Honour <hi>to be,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your faithfully devoted ſervant, John Robinſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:115543:5"/>
            <head>To the READER by R. J.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHat ſays <hi>Copernicus,</hi> that th' earth runs round?</l>
               <l>We grant it now, for never were there found</l>
               <l>Such topſey-turvey turnings as here be,</l>
               <l>Where all things ſpeak out mutability.</l>
               <l>Look further yet, and then within thine eye</l>
               <l>Its ſeverall cauſes do preſented lye.</l>
               <l>Only the moving cauſe, our ſin, you'l find</l>
               <l>Moves not at all, ſo hardned is our mind;</l>
               <l>This <hi>Achan</hi> troubles us: Oh! here's our Hell:</l>
               <l>And could we turn from this all would be wel.</l>
               <l>For 'tis not alwayes dark, ſee where in ſight</l>
               <l>Comes day-break in for to relieve the night.</l>
               <l>Live then a while by faith; It's Gods decree</l>
               <l>To deal forth earthly things unſteadily.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Miſtakes.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Pag. 10. <hi>line</hi> 12. for, from; him, read from him,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 23. <hi>l.</hi> 11. after ſheepfold, inſert (But the dunghill)</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 90. <hi>l.</hi> laſt: for this, read thus.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="abstract">
            <pb facs="tcp:115543:6"/>
            <list>
               <head>The <hi>Analyſis</hi> of it, ſetting briefly before you</head>
               <item>1 What this Viciſſitude is.</item>
               <item>2 The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſitudes in humane things, by
<list>
                     <item>1 Eminent places of Scripture.</item>
                     <item>2 Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hem in
<list>
                           <item>1 Politick Eſtates and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: whether
<list>
                                 <item>drawn out in length, as in Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies. or</item>
                                 <item>drawn up ſhort, as in Cities and their demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craticall govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 Families or deſcents.</item>
                           <item>3 Particular Perſons; conſidered in reſpect of their
<list>
                                 <item>Minds.</item>
                                 <item>Bodies.</item>
                                 <item>Eſtates.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115543:6"/>
3 The Cauſes of Viciſſitudes: which are
<list>
                     <item>Fictitious, or ſuppoſed only; as
<list>
                           <item>Fortune.</item>
                           <item>Fare.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>True and reall. and here we conſider
<list>
                     <item>1 Their Efficient cauſes; which are
<list>
                           <item>1 Principall God.</item>
                           <item>2 Leſſe princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal. and this is
<list>
                                 <item>1 Impulſive, Sin.</item>
                                 <item>2 Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall. as
<list>
                                       <item>1 The motion and influence of the heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bodies.</item>
                                       <item>2 The will of man.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 Their Ends or Final Cauſes.
<list>
                           <item>1 In reſpect of God, who ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances his own glory by them in the manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of the attributes, of
<list>
                                 <item>1 his Power.</item>
                                 <item>2 his Truth.</item>
                                 <item>3 his Wiſdome and Goodneſs.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 In reſpect of us; and theſe are,
<list>
                                 <item>1 to confirm our faith.</item>
                                 <item>2 to reform our lives.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115543:7"/>
4 The Uſes of them: and they are
<list>
                     <item>1 To wean our hearts from the love of the World, which is ſo unſetled.</item>
                     <item>2 To take us off from pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it above ourbrethren when we are in a proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous eſtate; as if either
<list>
                           <item>1 Our preſent great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe would never faile us. or,</item>
                           <item>2 The goodneſſe of our cauſe or Perſons were to be certainly meaſured by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain rule of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe and proſperity in worldly things.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 To keep us from deſpair in an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted condition, by exerciſing our faith and patience,</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115543:7"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>PROV. 27. ver. 1. and laſt branch of it.</bibl> 
                  <hi>For thou know'ſt not what a</hi> Day <hi>may bring forth.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>The whole Verſe runs thus; <q>
                  <hi>Boaſt not of to Morrow; for thou know'ſt not what a</hi> Day <hi>may bring forth.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His verſe is one of <hi>Solomons</hi> Proverbs ſpoken of 1 <hi>Reg.</hi> 4. 32. where we read that <hi>Solomon ſpake three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Proverbs, and his Songs were a thouſand and five.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now a Proverb is a ſpeech of an Abſolute and Independent nature. For which cauſe I ſhall not look back upon it as any ways Relative, but as ſtanding by it ſelf upon its own account.</p>
            <p>And in this Proverb two generall things are conſiderable.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A Prohibition, <hi>Boaſt not of to morrow.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. A Reaſon of it, <hi>For thou knoweſt not, &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And in the Reaſon there are three Particulars obſervable.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Birth: And this is implied in the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive <hi>Quid,</hi> which hath alwayes an <hi>Aliquid</hi> it relates unto, <hi>viz.</hi> ſome good or evil to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd of.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Parent that brings it forth: And this is <hi>A Day,</hi> or every particular <note place="margin">Veritas temporis filia, Aul. Gell. Noct. Attic. lib. 12. cap. 12.</note> day. For as Truth is the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Time; ſo alſo is Falſhood. It is Time that brings forth
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115543:8"/>
Births that are diverſly ſhapen, both good and evill, ſtrait and crooked, beautifull and defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, perfectly membred and monſtrous. Our <hi>Gazetts</hi> and <hi>Diurnals</hi> can ſatisfie us thus far.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Perſons that do ignorantly gaze after the Birth: And they are every man, <hi>Tu homo.</hi> And if it be ask'd then Who doth know it; it is anſwered, Only <hi>tu Domine.</hi> For <hi>ſecret things belong to the Lord,</hi> ſayes <hi>Moſes:</hi> And fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 28. 28.</note> things are thoſe ſecrets that God hath kept lock'd up from us in his own Boſome; He only knowing them <hi>a parte ante,</hi> we but <hi>a parte poſt.</hi> For as <hi>Bildad</hi> ſays, ſo may we, <hi>Heſterni ſumus,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Job. 8. 9.</note> That <hi>we are but Yeſterdayes off-ſpring and know nothing,</hi> no, not ſo much as the iſſue of one Day, what it will produce. <hi>Thou Know'ſt not what a Day may bring forth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here I ſhall begin with the laſt of the three, viz. The perſons that do ignorantly gaze after the Birth; And they are Every man; <hi>Tu homo.</hi> And the rather becauſe it is firſt in the Text, and comprehenſive of the reſt. The ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance whereof I ſhall hold out unto you in two Propoſitions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That no man can tell the Future Event of things, no not for a day: and this comes to paſſe from the great viciſſitude and unconſtancy of all worldly things. Or elſe, if I may but take in this Reaſon into the Propoſition, then I ſhall run it thus;</p>
            <p>That there is ſuch a Viciſſitude and Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy in all Sublunary things, as that a man can have no aſſurance of them, no not for a day. We know not what a Day may bring forth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:115543:8"/>
For in the great Houſe of the World there be three Roomes; whereof the upper and lower have no change, nor ſhadow of change, the one being full of eternall Glory, the other of Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; only this middle-moſt is fill'd with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Inſtability.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That it is God alone knows all future things. For this word <hi>Thou</hi> is here put <hi>ſignan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> with an <hi>Emphaſis</hi> upon it: <hi>Thou know'ſt not.</hi> As if he had ſaid, Though the Knowledge of all Contingencies be hid from Man, yet are they known to God as if they were preſent. For which cauſe God hath his Name from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, <hi>I am that I am;</hi> there being with him neither <note place="margin">Exod. 3. 14.</note> time paſt, nor time to come, but all being preſent.</p>
            <p>Firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen for the former of the two.</p>
            <p>Now for the orderly handling of this, that I may give ſome ſtays and reſts to your memories, I ſhall lay before you theſe five things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. What this Viciſſitude is.</item>
               <item>2. That there is ſuch a Viciſſitude.</item>
               <item>3. The Efficient Cauſes of it.</item>
               <item>4. The Ends or Final Cauſes of it.</item>
               <item>5. The Uſes of it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The firſt thing then is, <hi>Quid ſit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where know that by Viciſſitude here I do not <note place="margin">I</note> underſtand ſuch a mutation as is the utter anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilation of the Creatures Eſſence and Being; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God having made all things, doth not ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deſtroy any thing that he hath made, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of S. <hi>Paul</hi> 1 Cor. 7. 31. <hi>The faſhion of the world paſſes away, (fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gura mundi, non natura,</hi> as <hi>Aretius</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aretius</hi> in locum.</note> gloſſes it;) But ſuch a one as doth
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115543:9"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> alter it in its preſent eſtate and condition; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> particular eſtate and condition of a thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ing the proper object of Viciſſitude. Neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> again every mutation of a things particular eſtate and condition that is the proper object of Viciſſitude, but only ſuch a mutation as is reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procall: <hi>i. e.</hi> ſuch a change, as hath like the Sea its <hi>Flu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> and <hi>Refluxus,</hi> its Ebbings and Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings from one eſtate to another. And this too we do not underſtand in a Morall, but in a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall way. For there may be a Morall change from good to evil, and back again from evil to good, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et we cannot call by the name of Viciſſitude. But the Viciſſitude here ſpoken of is only in Naturall and Worldly things, which have ſuch a circular motion here, and are ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant in it, as that there can be no Inſurance made of them in this great Exchange of the World, becauſe we know not concerning them what a day may bring forth. And ſo much for the firſt thing.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is the Demonſtration of this <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Truth, That there is ſuch a Viciſſitude.</p>
            <p>And this I ſhall do, Firſt, by expreſſe places of Scripture. Secondly, by ſome Inſtances of it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, by ſome expreſſe places of Scripture. And herethe Preacher hath a good ſaying, <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtes</hi> 7. 14. <hi>In the day of Proſperity be joyfull, but in the day of Adverſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> conſider.</hi> And the thing we are to conſider of is, <hi>That God hath ſet the one over againſt the other.</hi> His meaning is, That God hath ordered things here with a great deal of change and variety; As that he hath ſet Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity over againſt Adverſity, and again, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity over againſt Proſperity, even as Light
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115543:9"/>
and Darkneſſe, to ſucceed each <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant intercourſe: <hi>To the end,</hi> ſays he, <hi>That man ſhould find nothing after him:</hi> i. e. that ſo by this interchangeable dealing of God, no man ſhould be able to find out infallibly what his after e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate ſhall be in this world, whether happy or elſe miſerable. Again conſult that of S. <hi>Paul</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 31. where the world <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Videtar bic allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſſe ad Scenas, in quibus a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>laea momento compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal a novam red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt faciem.</hi> Calvin. <hi>in locum,</hi> Nemo eſt Qui Deum credat ſibi tam faven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinum ut poſſit ſibi polli. eri. Sen. Thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt. trag. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and all things in it are compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a Scene in a Comedy, which being changed on the ſuddain, ſome new matter is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently preſented to the eyes of the Spectatours. And S. <hi>James</hi> again to the ſame purpoſe <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. &amp; 14. <hi>Go to,</hi> &amp;c. The ſpeech is Ironicall, as deriding thoſe who think all things here below to be of a ſtanding nature: when as the wheel of all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunary things is ſo turning, that a man cannot tell what turn ſhall be on the morrow. That as the Scripture ſayes of <note n="*" place="margin">Ita. 22. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Shebna,</hi> That God ſhould turn and toſſe <note place="margin">Huic affine eſt il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud Plautinum, Enim vero, dii nos quaſi pilas, homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes habe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Plaut. in Capt. Scen. 1.</note> him like a Ball: ſo are all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things turn'd and toſs'd up and down by the Racket of Gods Power, and Providence, even as a man rackets a ball to &amp; fro from one place to another.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſhall demonſtrate this by ſeverall inſtances. And <note place="margin">O ſi poſſemus in talem aſcendero ſocculam, ut to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Orbis osten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derem ruinas. Hieron. l. 2. ad Heliod.</note> here methinks I could wiſh with S. <hi>Jerom,</hi> that I were now in the top of ſuch a Watch-tower, that I might diſcover unto you the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines and alterations of all things
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115543:10"/>
in the world, from the beginning of the Creation to this day; and preſent this lively to your eyes, which I am fain to do now only to your minds and underſtandings; that ſo I might be able to ſay with the prophet <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 46. 8. <hi>Come and behold the works of the Lord, what deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> ſo what changes and alterations, <hi>he hath wrought in the world!</hi> For <hi>one generation,</hi> ſays the Preacher, <hi>is paſſing away, and another comes:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſt. 1. 4.</note> neither is there any thing here ſo fix'd, that it can ſay of it ſelf as the falſe Prophets did, <hi>Erit ſicut</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 56. laſt. Sic vulg. Latin.</note> 
               <hi>hodie, ſic &amp; cras, Tomorrow ſhall be with me as this day;</hi> Since no man knows what a day may bring forth. Now this I ſhall hold out unto you in a threefold reſpect, that ye may be the more affected with it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in relation to Politick Eſtates and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to continued Families, or Races of men that are lineally ſucceſſive for Name and Greatneſſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to particular Perſons.</p>
            <p>In all which if I be more hiſtoricall then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe I would, it muſt be imputed to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Subject, which is of that nature, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires it of me.</p>
            <p>Firſt then I ſhall conſider it in relation to Politick Eſtates and Governments: whether we conſider them either as drawn out in length in Monarchies; or elſe as drawn up ſhort in Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which are nothing elſe but Empires epito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mized, or Republicks bound up in a leſſer vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume.</p>
            <p>Firſt then I ſhall demonſtrate this unto you in Monarchies, which <hi>Bodine</hi> tells us are more du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durable <note place="margin">Lib. 4. de cep. c. 1.</note>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115543:10"/>
then Popular States, becauſe leſſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to be divided, (Unity being the great Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of all things:) and yet have theſe had, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dies, hora, momentum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertendis dominationibus ſufficit, quae adamanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis credebantur radicibus eſſe fundatae.</hi> Sir Walt. Rawl. preface out of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaub.</note> as the Moon, not only their increaſe and full light, but alſo their wain and changes, and this ſometimes in a moment. That as in Muſick you ſhall hear ſometimes a ſtring tun'd up to its <hi>ultimum potentiae,</hi> as high as it will bear, and preſently depreſſed again to the loweſt Key, and another elevated, yet both of them breathing but light aires and of ſhort continuance: So may you ſee a Monarchy now wound up to the higheſt pitch of Happineſs, and by and by let down a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain into the loweſt <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Regnorum initia, incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eum &amp; occaſus à De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pendent.</hi> Phil. de Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes lib. 7.</note> depths of miſery. This is the Lords doing, and it is marvellous in our eyes.</p>
            <p>And here I ſhall begin with thoſe Empires and Monarchies that were moſt famous among the reſt.</p>
            <p>For how ſoon was the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> or <hi>Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> Monarchy ſwallow'd up by the <hi>Perſian,</hi> the <hi>Perſian</hi> by the <hi>Greek</hi> or <hi>Macedonian</hi> Empire, and the <hi>Greek</hi> by the <hi>Roman?</hi> which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Daniel</hi> preſents unto us by the Gold, Silver, Braſſe and Iron whereof <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage conſiſted, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. 32. The diſſolution of one, as in naturall things, ſo here, being ſtill the generation of another; and again the erection of the later being the deſtruction of the former.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:115543:11"/>
And as for the <hi>Romane</hi> Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, their own Hiſtorian can tell <note place="margin">1. Flor. <hi>in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditu ad</hi> hiſt.</note> us of that, how it had both its Infancy, Youth, Manhood, and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Imperiorum nunc floret for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuna, nunc ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſcit, nunc in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terit,</hi> Pater<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. hiſt. lib. 2.</note> Old age as it were by turnes. As its Infancy under Kings, its Youth under Conſuls, its Manhood from the firſt <hi>Punick</hi> warre unto the time of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> and from that time its Old age under the ſucceeding Emperours; untill at length that ſolid Body was torn aſunder by the ſtruglings of her own Children, into the Eaſtern and Weſtern Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires, whereof the former was ſoon eaten out by the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Saracens,</hi> and the later alſo fell away much after a little revolution of time, by the falling off of divers Nations from her, each of which after they had pluck'd off their own feathers from the <hi>Roman</hi> Eagle, left her al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt naked; As the <hi>Franks</hi> and <hi>Burgundians</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> the <hi>Goths</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> the <hi>Normans</hi> and <hi>Lombards</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> together with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> in <hi>Britain:</hi> untill at the laſt caſt the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy began a little to recall her ſelf into <hi>Germany,</hi> where ſhe hath held up ſince little more then the bare name of the Empire. So that Viciſſitude you ſee is the great Empreſſe of the world, unto whoſe unſtay'd dominion all earthly Powers and Principalities muſt be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, even thoſe that are of the firſt Magnitude, much more others that move in a lower Orbe.</p>
            <p>And of theſe I ſhall ſingle out only three, which I conceive moſt eminent, to be inſtanced in for this point.</p>
            <p>The firſt is <hi>Judea,</hi> whoſe government was
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115543:11"/>
Monarchically ſettled by God himſelf; yet how <note place="margin">See 1 Sam. cap. 10.</note> oft did ſhe change her Lords and Maſters, yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her ſelf as it were ſucceſſively firſt to the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonian,</hi> and after that to the <hi>Roman, Perſian, Saracen, Chriſtian, Aegyptian,</hi> and now to the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> power? That as the <note n="*" place="margin">Ovid.</note> Poet ſpake of <hi>Troy; fuit Ilium;</hi> ſo may we of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> her <hi>Metropolis, fuit Hieroſolyma,</hi> that <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> was, She <hi>was great among the Nations,</hi> or <note place="margin">Lam. 1. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Domina Gentium, the Lady of the Nations,</hi> as the Vulgar <hi>Latin</hi> reads it. But now, <hi>Non ſic ut olim,</hi> It hath not been with her for theſe many generations paſt <hi>as in former days,</hi> (to uſe <hi>Job's</hi> words in his twenty ninth chapter, ſecond and third verſes) <hi>when God preſerv'd her, when his Candle ſhined upon her head, and when by that light ſhe walk'd through darkneſſe;</hi> but <hi>Servants</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lam. 5. 8.</note> 
               <hi>have ruled over her, and there was none to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver her out of their hands.</hi> Which is a good le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of Mutability to other Kingdomes and their Mother-cities. For <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was once a holy and happy city, and had been happy ſtill, had ſhe but continued holy; but that failing, <hi>How</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lam. 4. 1.</note> 
               <hi>is her Gold become dimme, how is her fine Gold chang'd into Droſſe!</hi> as ſhe complains her ſelf.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Example I produce here is <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">As <hi>Pertinax</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour was call'd <hi>Pila For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunae; Nam quod Ethni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci Fortunam, nos Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ani providentiam appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi> Aurel. Vict. Epitom.</note> which we may well call the Ball of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: And indeed ſo it was, being bandyed from one Lord to another ten ſeverall times, before it came to lie (as now it doth) at the foot of <hi>Spain.</hi> For being a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey at firſt diverſly peopled, it was upon the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115543:12"/>
allotted to the Eaſtern Emperours, but from them forc'd by the <hi>Almains,</hi> and ſo to the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Saracens,</hi> and then ſucceſſively hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried about to the <hi>Normans, Germans, French, Hungarians, Arragonoys,</hi> and from them to the <hi>French</hi> again; till in the end the <hi>Spaniard</hi> ſeiſed upon it: and whether it will continue long with him or no, is very uncertain; eſpecially if we remember how of late years a poor Fiſherman, <hi>(Maſſionello</hi> by <note place="margin">See <hi>Howels</hi> rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it lately printed.</note> name) ſnatch'd up the reines of Government from; him &amp; (had not God otherwiſe determined of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome by infatuating that Muſhrome King) for ought we know, he might have runne quite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with them, ſo ſlippery are all earthly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes!</p>
            <p>3. But not to look out any longer to other nations of <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> (methinks) we may inſtance this beſt by reflecting upon our ſelves. For you all know (I ſuppoſe) how the <hi>Romans, Saxons, Danes</hi> and <hi>Normans</hi> had each of them their ſeverall and alternate dayes of Lordſhip over this Nation; but yet becauſe they did not know in thoſe their days the things that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long'd unto their Peace, how do we ſee the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows of the night ſtretched out upon them, their Suns ſet with us, and their days ſhut in!</p>
            <p>The longeſt day we read of was that in <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſudh</hi>'s <note place="margin">Joſh. 10. 13.</note> time, wherein though the Sun ſtood ſtill in <hi>Gibeon</hi> for the ſpace of a whole day, yet ſet it did at laſt.</p>
            <p>The day of the <hi>Romans</hi> was long upon our Horizon, for the <note place="margin">See our <hi>Engl. Chronicle.</hi>
               </note> Sun of their proſperity ſhone
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115543:12"/>
here for the ſpace of four hundred years and more; Yet did it then go down as to us in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Darkneſſe here now doth lie upon it.</p>
            <p>Again, the day of the <hi>Saxons</hi> continued five hundred years and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards; <note n="*" place="margin">So long they tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed here, but reign'donly twenty ſix under <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute, Harold</hi> and <hi>Hardie Canute.</hi>
               </note> That of the <hi>Danes</hi> two hundred fifty five years or there abouts.</p>
            <p>And how long the day of the <hi>Normans</hi> hath laſted every petty Almanack can tell us. I, and if none of thoſe Suns come to riſe again within our Hemiſphere (when the ſins of this Nation are ripe, and call for Gods ſickle to cut them down) its beſide his ordinary rule, which uſually runs out all humane things by a changeable cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference; for ſo <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us in his book of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes, That the Sun riſes, and the Sun</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Chap. 1. verſ. 5.</note> 
               <hi>goes down, &amp; haſteth to the place where he aroſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither is this all, that the Powers and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities on earth are upon a daily turn, but as the <hi>Primum Mobile</hi> (you know) carries about the other Spheres; ſo do theſe carry about many other changes and alterations with them: As that of Religion, Laws, Liberties, Sciences, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms and ſuch like. Nay, even the Houſes of God, which before to violate was held a crime inexpiable, yet are they now upon ſuch removes broken down without ſcruple; and the very <note place="margin">The beathen therefore did ſupe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cribe their Urn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thus, <hi>Diis manibus Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crum:</hi> And the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſet <hi>Deo Opt. Max. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crum</hi> upon their To<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bes and Graveſtones.</note> Urns of the Dead, which have been alwayes look'd upon as ſacred Cabinets to preſerve the bodies of Gods Saints in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115543:13"/>
for Eternity, yet are they now broken up, and their Aſhes thrown about (ſuch is the unſetled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of all things here below) even as the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt Duſt upon the face of the earth.</p>
            <p>Beloved, it hath been ever thus upon the converſion of ſuch great bodies, and it is ſo ſtill: For never was <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Res Deus Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtras celeri cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas turbine ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſavit.</hi> Sen. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hyeſt.</note> there any converſion in this Land like to that our eyes have ſeen of late; That if any one ſhould have ſlept but ſome few years laſt paſt (as the Ancients fain of <hi>Epimenides)</hi> and ſhould <note place="margin">Quinquaginta annos dorm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſſe fingitur.</note> have awaked again in theſe times, how would he wonder at thoſe ſtrange <hi>Metamorphoſes</hi> that are now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, there being <hi>Nova rerum facies,</hi> A new face of things both in Church and State! Inſomuch <note place="margin">I heard Mr <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> ſay, He ſought for <hi>Rome</hi> in <hi>Rome</hi> and could not find her. <hi>Juel</hi> in his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology, 2. part, diviſ. 21.</note> (as Mr <hi>Harding</hi> ſpake ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times of <hi>Rome,</hi> That he did <hi>quaerere Romam in Roma,</hi> That he did ſeek <hi>Rome</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> and could not find it,) ſo may we ſay now, That we may <hi>quoerere Angliam in Anglia,</hi> That we may now ſeek for old <hi>England</hi> in our new <hi>England,</hi> and yet go without it, it is ſo much chang'd from what it was before.</p>
            <p>And as we have ſeen much of this already, ſo who knows but we may come to ſee a great deal more hereafter? Since we know not what a Day may bring forth.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Neither is this true only in Empires and Monarchies, but alſo in Cities and their
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115543:13"/>
popular Governments. <hi>Etiam ſummis negatum eſt urbibus ſtare diu,</hi> ſays the Moraliſt. And to <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> this purpoſe tends that of the Authour to the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cain</hi> therefore ſayes Saint <hi>Augustine,</hi> built a city, but <hi>Abel</hi> none <hi>Civitas e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim Sanctorum ſuperna.</hi> Lib. 15. <hi>de Civit. Dei</hi> cap. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Hebrews,</hi> Heb. 13. 14. <hi>We have here no abiding city, but we look for one to come, whoſe founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is in the heavens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is then no City on earth, nor any kind of Government in it that ever ſtood up long in one poſture, none that ever was, or ſhall be abiding. <hi>Paſſeye up to</hi> Calneh <hi>and ſee,</hi> ſaies the Prophet, <hi>Amos 6. 2. and from hence go to</hi> Hemath <hi>the Great, and ſo to</hi> Gath <hi>of the</hi> Philiſtins. So paſſe ye up to <hi>Athens,</hi> the eye of <hi>Greece</hi> for Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and humane Literature, and ſee, and from thence go to <hi>Rome,</hi> the head of the Weſtern Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and ſo come to <hi>Florence,</hi> the beauty of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly;</hi> (for I forbear to name more, Examples in this kinde being almoſt infinite) in all which you may read this truth at large.</p>
            <p>And firſt for <hi>Athens:</hi> How many changes of Governours and Governments did ſhe endure? putting her ſelf off from hereditary Kings to Archons, or Ariſtocraticall Lords, who govern'd firſt for terme of life, then decennially, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theſe to Democraticall Rulers.</p>
            <p>Next for <hi>Rome;</hi> how oft hath that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>By</hi> Brennus <hi>King of the</hi> Gauls <hi>Anno Mundi 3562; By</hi> Alaricus <hi>King of the</hi> Goths <hi>An. Chriſt. 410. By</hi> Genſericus <hi>King of the</hi> Vandals 447. <hi>&amp;c. and by the Duke of</hi> Butbon <hi>An. 1527. vide plura in</hi> Bucholcer. <hi>chronol.</hi>
               </note> city been alter'd by <hi>Gauls, Hunnes, Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandals?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea how oft hath the Government of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115543:14"/>
it been paſs'd away from one hand to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>It is myſtically repreſented to us <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. 3. by the Beaſt of ſeven heads, which is there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted by the ſeven Hills it is built upon, to be <hi>Rome:</hi> And <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idèo dicta est</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma <hi>urbs Septicallis,</hi> Godwin Antiq. <hi>lib. 1. cap. 1.</hi>
               </note> according to the number of thoſe Hills, to ſo many ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters did it ſubmit it ſelf, who had their ſeverall turnes of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme power and regiment o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Tacit. <hi>ad initium hiſt.</hi>
               </note> her; as <hi>Kings, Conſuls, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators, Decemviri, Tribunes, Emperous</hi> and <hi>Popes:</hi> under the laſt of which I do not find that <note place="margin">Downh. <hi>de</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tich. <hi>lib. 1. c. 4.</hi>
               </note> it was ever beſieged by any that took it not; ſuch ſtrange ebbings hath that Sea had experience of!</p>
            <p>Laſt of all for <hi>Florence.</hi> It is ſtrange to tell what various whirlings about that hath had in point of ſupreme rule and power. For at firſt the Nobility ruled it in an Ariſtocraticall way. But a little after ſome Grandees among the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple wreſted it to themſelves: who being tired out with continuall quarrellings one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, (for the people were divided into three ranks) the middle ſort of them took upon them the management of the State. And theſe alſo falling quickly together by the eares, the third and loweſt ſort became maſters of it. Which holding not long by reaſon of their mutuall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, they yield themſelves and the government of their <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Machiavil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Hiſt. of</hi> Florence.</note> City unto <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> brother to <hi>Lewis</hi> the ninth;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115543:14"/>
who within a ſhort time being invited to the Kingdome of <hi>Naples,</hi> and leaving only Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties at <hi>Florence,</hi> the <hi>Florentines</hi> return to their Popular Government, and renew their civill warres among themſelves. For redreſſe where of they ſend for the Duke of <hi>Athens,</hi> and give up all to him. But ſhortly they ſuppoſing themſelves to be brought in bondage, and to be deſpoiled of their liberty by the fear of his guard, baniſh him the City, and within leſſe then one years ſpace ſhake off his government over them. After which they come to an Ariſtocracie again, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing new Names and Officers for their Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and changing and rechanging them ſo oft, that ſometimes their State was no better or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd then if it had been committed to mad men or children without diſcretion, the city ſcarce twenty yeares together keeping the ſame forme of State: but as ſick men in fevers (ſays <note n="*" place="margin">Lib. 4. de Rep. cap. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus)</hi> deſire to be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved now hither, and by and by thither, or from <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quid refert quod alibi fuerit oeger, cum non ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, locumve mutârit, cum non exuat oegritudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem?</hi> Lipſius de Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Quocunque oegrum tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuleris, ſecum morbum transferet.</hi> Sen. Epiſt. 17.</note> one bed to another, as if the diſeaſe were in the places where they lay, and not in the intralls of their own bodies; ſo were the <hi>Florentines</hi> ſtill turning their State, till they turnd it into the hands of the <hi>Medices,</hi> who now hold it. A thing almoſt incredible (ſays he) did not their own Recorder leave it recorded to poſterity.</p>
            <p>But in the ſecond place let us deſcend to Families or Races of men that are li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neally
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115543:15"/>
ſucceſſive for Name and Greatneſſe.</p>
            <p>And here let me ask, where are thoſe Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Families cried up ſo much in former times, and famous in their generations?</p>
            <p>As the Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the <hi>Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabees</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eight</hi> Maceabean <hi>Princes and Kings ſwayd the ſceptre of</hi> Jewry <hi>one after another: So alſo did eleven</hi> Ptolemies <hi>in</hi> Aegypt, <hi>till the</hi> Romans <hi>made themſelves heires to it.</hi>
               </note> in <hi>Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and of the <hi>Ptolemies</hi> in <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, where <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> Zelzuccian <hi>Line or Family gave way to the</hi> Oguzian <hi>or</hi> Ottoman <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily that now reigns: So did the</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laeologi <hi>after ſeven ſucceſſions.</hi>
               </note> is the <hi>Zelzuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi> Family in the leſſer <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> and the Imperiall Family of the <hi>Palaeologi</hi> in <hi>Greece?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That of the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>There were</hi> 21 <hi>Kings of this line in</hi> France <hi>one after another deſcended from</hi> Meroveus; <hi>Theſe yielded to</hi> Pip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pin <hi>the firſt of the ſecond race, whoſe line ended in</hi> Ludovic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <hi>the fifth; and then came in the</hi> Capets, <hi>the preſent King being the thirtieth from</hi> Hugh Capet, <hi>and of the</hi> F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ench <hi>bloud.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rovignians</hi> in <hi>France?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of the <hi>Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagenets</hi> in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Name and Glory of the</hi> Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genets <hi>was ſwallow'd up of the</hi> Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors <hi>in</hi> Henry <hi>the ſeventh, who mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried</hi> Elizabeth <hi>the Heir of the</hi> York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh <hi>Houſe.</hi> Hell. Geogr.</note> more of this rank I might name, did not the narow com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of ſo ſmall a Treatiſe bound me?</p>
            <p>Tell me, is not the Name and Greatneſſe of theſe Families long ſince expired, the Roots and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115543:15"/>
Branches of them quite remov'd, and others planted in their roomes? Examples of this ſort are innumerable, as <hi>Elihu</hi> ſaies in <hi>Job: He breaks in pieces mighty men without number;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Job 34. 24.</note> (ſo mighty Families without number) <hi>and ſets up others in their ſtead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for ſuch Families as are of a lower forme, we need not go farre, ſince our own knowledge here will lead us to continuall chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and alterations.</p>
            <p>For thou haſt ſeen it may be many Families heretofore in this Nation, brim full of earthly happineſſe, and running over; and now upon thy ſecond view of them behold there is no ſuch thing, but they are much alter'd, and running very low in the world, if not clean run out.</p>
            <p>So that proſperity (you ſee) was never yet ſo entail'd upon any Family, and the Heirs thereof, but within a little time ſome one or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath cut it off.</p>
            <p>But laſt of all, if we look upon particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſons, this will appear moſt evident; but eſpecially if we conſider them three wayes. In reſpect of their Bodies, Minds, and Eſtates.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> hath an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ſaying of the two former <note place="margin">In his Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion de Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritu Sancto.</note> joyntly conſider'd, which is this; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>i. e.</hi> We are not mixt creatures only, but alſo contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry both to others and our ſelves: not continuing truly the ſame no not ſo much as one day; but both in regard of our bodies and minds
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115543:16"/>
perpetually flowing and perpetually changing.</p>
            <p>And we can inſtance this in all the ſtages of our life, wherein by the ordinary courſe of nature, we are firſt weak, and then ſtrong, and after weak again. As in our Childhood we are then weak both in Body and Mind; in our Youth, ſtrong in Body and weak in Mind; and in our Manhood ſtrong in both; but in our Old age ſtrong in Mind and weak in Body; and in our Decrepit, weak again in both, as we were <note place="margin">Senes bis pueri.</note> in our Childhood at the firſt.</p>
            <p>But to leave this generall conſideration of them, and to look upon them now more diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſeverally by themſelves. And firſt for the change of particular Perſons in regard of their Bodies.</p>
            <p>And here it is true of them what <hi>Seneca</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, <note place="margin">In his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>no man is the ſame to day, he was yeſterday: Ego ipſe</hi> (ſays he) <hi>dum haec lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor mutari, mutatus ſum.</hi> Our Bodies (ſays he) are like a River, which keeps nothing but the bare name that was firſt given it; for as touching the preſent individuall matter which is the watry ſubſtance of it, this is alwayes tranſient, and other comes into its room: And ſo it is with the Body of man, which is alwayes receiving in new air and life, and venting the former. Which makes <hi>David</hi> profeſſe of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that he was toſs'd up and down like the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſt; and <hi>Job</hi> compare man for his bodily ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to a Flower that never continues in one ſtay, <hi>Job</hi> 14. 2. For now we are ſtrong, and by and by weak; now beautifull, and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deformed. A little Fit of the Feaver, Small Pox, or the like, alters us ſo, as if we were
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115543:16"/>
not the ſame men we were before; inſomuch that we hear ſome ſpeaking thus unto us,—<hi>Heu</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ovid.</note> 
               <hi>quantum mutatus ab illo!</hi> Alas, how hath this fit alter'd you from what you were in your health! for how are your lips grown pallid, your cheeks diſcolour'd, your eyes ſunck into their holes, and your face quite disfigur'd! And o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers there be of our acquaintance that like <hi>Jobs</hi> three friends do lift up their eyes afarre off, <note place="margin">Job 2. 12.</note> and know us not; ſo much are we chang'd in reſpect of our Bodies!</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, Let us conſider it alſo in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of mens minds.</p>
            <p>And here (to ſay nothing of a morall <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rebus cunctis inest qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam velut Orbis, ut quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admodum temporu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vices, ita &amp; Morum vertan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur:</hi> Tacit. Annal. lib. 3.</note> change, which is obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous every where) as on the one ſide we find nothing more notable <hi>Quinquennio Neronis,</hi> then the firſt five years of <hi>Nero's</hi> Reigne, and more excellent then his Youth; Yet afterwads having well taſted the ſweet morſell of Soveraignty, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came <note place="margin">Bodin. <hi>de rep.</hi> lib. 4. cap. 1.</note> (ſays one) the moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable Tyrant that ever was: And ſo alſo of <hi>Herod</hi> the Great <hi>Philo</hi> ſays, that he reign'd ſix years as a good and juſt Prince, preſenting the <hi>Protaſis</hi> of his Reign with a large Fringe of Goodneſſe about it; (as <hi>Joaz, Amazias,</hi> and <hi>Ozias</hi> did) but as for the <hi>Cataſtrophe</hi> of it, that was very ſad and fearfull. So on the other ſide, we find <hi>Manaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoh</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> ſoaking the forepart of their lives in blood, being no better at firſt then
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115543:17"/>
               <hi>Nero</hi> was at the laſt, even a piece of clay temper'd with bloud; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lutum fanguine commixtum.</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eton. <hi>in vita.</hi>
               </note> yet was their end like the end of <hi>Davids</hi> good man, <hi>The end of that man is peace.</hi> Pſal. 37. 37. But to wave theſe, (whereof much might be ſaid, did it not quite lye out of my road I am now in.) and to inſiſt only upon the changea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe that doth naturally adhere to the Mind of man.</p>
            <p>Now tell me, if any thing in the world may be ſaid to be more moveable then the Mind of man.</p>
            <p>It is a ſpirituall ſubſtance, and ſo is alwayes moving (though inſenſibly) from one thing unto another, never reſting, untill at laſt like <hi>Noah</hi>'s dove it be taken into the Heavenly Ark. S. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Talis eſt mens cum pennas acceperit.</hi> Homil. 22. <hi>ad</hi> Hebraeos.</note> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> therefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares it to a Bird which flies in a moment of time over mountains and hills, over ſeas and rocks, without any hindrance: for now it is upon the loweſt Shrub, and preſently upon the higheſt branch of the talleſt Cedar; now upon heavenly, and within the twinkling of an eye upon earthly things; now at <hi>Dan,</hi> and in a trice at <hi>Beerſheba;</hi> now at one part of the earth and then at another; for ſometimes it is ſoring after <hi>Principalities and Powers, and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eph. 6. 12</note> 
               <hi>Wickedneſſes in high places,</hi> as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaks, then after Riches, and by and by after Pleaſures; now rejoycing, and then ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing; now quieted, and immediately trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and as ſoon pacified again; now ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115543:17"/>
and ſtraightway fearing thoſe hopes; now loving, and then hating what it loved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: <hi>Sic omnia mutabilitati ſubjacent</hi> (ſaies Saint <hi>Auguſtine.)</hi> Thus do all things lie down <note place="margin">In his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>quy.</note> under mutability! And it amazed Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Illud ſupra modum ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendum, quod ſub eodem momento contrariis affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctibus diſtrabor;</hi> Bern. <hi>de inter. dom.</hi> c. 64. <hi>ubi plura.</hi>
               </note> much to conſider how in the ſame moment of time his mind was not only diverſly, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe contrarily affected, and as it were pull'd a pieces betwixt love and hatred, joy and ſorrow, fear and hope, having as many varieties of affections within him, as there were diverſities of things in the world for them to light upon.</p>
            <p>So that you ſee how the ſeverall Paſſions of our Minds do in a breath, and with the turning of a hand ſtreere divers wayes, firſt looking one way and then another, according as they are wheeled about with the motions of outward Contingencies.</p>
            <p>But in the laſt place we ſhall adde unto the former the great changes that particular men are ſubject to in regard of their outward Eſtates <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Habet ſuas vices conditio mortalium, ut adverſa ex ſecundis, ex adverſis iti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ſecunda naſcantur,</hi> Plin. jun. <hi>in his Pane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyr. to</hi> Trajan.</note> and Fortunes. For the condition of Mortals (ſays a heathen man) hath its turnes and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes, both of Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Adverſity.</p>
            <p>That as in a military skirmiſh there be ſome come up to diſcharge, while others fall off: ſo is it in the World's <hi>Militia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:115543:18"/>One there is that is raiſ'd out of the Duſt to ſit among Princes: whereas there is another that is ſlung down from the pinnacle of worldly joy and proſperity and ſtated, as <hi>Job</hi> was, upon the Dunghill. And this doth the Preacher tell us <note place="margin">Eceleſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt. cap. 4. ver. 14.</note> among the reſt of thoſe changes that fell under his obſervation, <hi>That one comes out of Priſon to reign,</hi> (as Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did out of the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to the Throne) <hi>whereas alſo there is he that is born in his Kingdome</hi> and <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes</hi> very <hi>poor;</hi> (as our <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 110.</note> the third was, while he lived ſomtimes on the Churches Alms.)</p>
            <p>God hath appointed us (ſaith one well) all our parts to play, <note place="margin">Sr Walt. Rawl. <hi>in Praef. to his hiſt. of the world.</hi>
               </note> and hath not in their diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution been either ſpare-hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the meaneſt, nor yet partiall to the greateſt.</p>
            <p>He gave <hi>Caius Marius</hi> at firſt the part of a Carpenters ſonne; but afterwards the part of one that was ſeven times Conſul. So alſo <hi>Agathocles</hi> the part of a Potters ſon at the firſt, but afterwards of the King of <hi>Sicily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So alſo on the other ſide <hi>Darius</hi> playd the part one while of the greateſt Emperour, and another time of the moſt miſerable Beggar, beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging but a little water to quench the drought of Death. And <hi>Bajazet</hi> playd the Grand Signior in the morning, but in the evening ſtood for <hi>Tamerlains</hi> footſtool.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Jane Shore, Edward</hi> the fourths Minion, acts now as Miſtreſſe of a ſtately Pallace, and a little after dies in a ditch for want of a houſe; and (as he ſaid of <hi>Icarus)</hi> ſo may we of <note place="margin">Ovid. Epiſt.</note>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:115543:18"/>
her, that—<hi>Nomina fecit aquis,</hi> ſhe gave name to the place where ſhe died, it being call'd from her <hi>Shore-ditch</hi> to this day.</p>
            <p>But I forbear, ſince there is enough recorded for our uſe in the ſacred Scriptures to this purpoſe; where we find an example of the one in <hi>David,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 78. 71.</note> who ſayes that God <hi>took him from following the Ewes with young,</hi> and ſet him upon the Throne; there <hi>to feed</hi> (as he ſays) Jacob <hi>his people, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>his inheritance.</hi> And to go lower yet, not only from the ſheepfold, ſo he ſays Pſal. 113. 7. and 8 verſes; <hi>God takes the poor out of the Duſt, and the needy out of the Dunghill: That he may ſet him among Princes, even with the Princes of his people:</hi> Now more vile <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sterquilinio ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectior.</hi> Eraſm. Adag. <hi>pag.</hi> 110.</note> and contemptible then the Duſt we tread upon, which the leaſt breath of wind commands any way, or then the worſt of duſt which is that of the Dunghill, we cannot be; yet theſe are they (ſays the <hi>Pſalmiſt)</hi> whom he ſets among Princes, even with the Princes of his people.</p>
            <p>An example of the other we have in <hi>Antiochus,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luxuriant animi re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus plerumque ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis,</hi> Ovid. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de</hi> Art. Amandi.</note> 2 Mac. 9. 9. who was ſo fill'd with Pride through the rankneſſe of his Proſperity, that he thought he might command the Sea, (ſo proud was he, ſayes the Text, beyond the condition of man) and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that he could weigh the Mountains in a ballance, and reach up to the ſtarres of heaven: Yet by and by is his combe cut, all
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115543:19"/>
his Glory worm-eaten, and none able to endure him for the filthineſſe of his ſmell.</p>
            <p>Adde to this the example of <hi>Balthazar,</hi> Dan. 5. 5. who was now carouſing in the conſecrated Veſſels that <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> his Grandfather had plundred the Temple of and Houſe of God at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as you may ſee 2 <hi>Kings</hi> chap. laſt. But in the ſame hour (ſaies the Text) came out the hand-writing of the wall againſt him, and then was the Kings countenance chang'd, his thoughts troubled, the joints of his loynes looſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and his Kingdome given away to the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus are we for outward things like ſo many Counters, which ſtand one while for a pound, and another for a penny.</p>
            <p>That as we ſee commonly in High-wayes, where one man hath ſet his foot, another pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently follows him and treads it out again; ſo is it uſually, That if one man beat out an Honour or <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nunc ager umbreni ſub nomine, nuper O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felli Dictus, ſed nulli pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prius—</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orat. ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rm. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Satyr.</hi> 2.</note> Eſtate to himſelf, another comes after and treads out that impreſſion, and whoſe it ſhall be next there is no man knows. Nay <hi>Lucan, Ipſa vices natura a ſubit—</hi>Even the whole courſe of nature runs about in a circular motion; Our Bodies, Minds, and outward felicities, whatſoever we are, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever we have, are all ſubject to change in ſuch wiſe, that we can have no aſſurance of them, no not for a day. We know not what a Day may bring forth.</p>
            <p>And ſo much for the demonſtration of this
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115543:19"/>
truth, <hi>viz.</hi> That there is ſuch a Viciſſitude.</p>
            <p>The next thing is the Efficient Cauſes of it. For we never know <note place="margin">3</note> any thing throughly, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Scire eſt per cauſam ſcire,</hi> Ariſt. phyſ. 2. cap. 3.</note> (ſays the Philoſopher) untill we know the Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of it.</p>
            <p>Now in ſpeaking to this, I ſhall proceed f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>irſt, negatively; ſecondly, affirmatively.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Negatively, in ſhewing what have been thought to be the cauſes of all Changes and Alterations, yet are not ſo indeed. And here the <hi>Epicures</hi> and vulgar Heathen have <note place="margin">
                  <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs omnia verſat,</hi> Virgil. Bucolic. Eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. 9.</note> thought <hi>Fortune</hi> to be the cauſe of them; And they define it thus, to be <hi>An Event of things without Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Si eventum nulla cauſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nexione productu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, caſum eſſe definias, nihil omnino caſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe confirmo.</hi> Boët. de conſol. philos. l. 5. <hi>proſ.</hi> 1.</note> it is to ſay that an Event of things without a Cauſe, ſhould be the Cauſe of all Events, judge ye.</p>
            <p>For it was only the ignorance of the true Cauſes that made the name of <hi>Fortune;</hi> there being nothing fortuitous in it ſelf, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to us and our ignorance; ſince the power and providence of God hath the ordering and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of all things here below. And this did the wiſer ſort among them confeſſe, as the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyriſt tells us.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Nullum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>umen abeſt ſi ſit prudentia, ſed te</l>
               <l>Nos facimus Fortuna Deam—<note place="margin">Juvenal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Satyr. 10.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:115543:20"/>
Others again, as the <hi>Stoicks,</hi> make <hi>Fate</hi> or <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Regitur fatis mortale ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, nec ſibi quiſquam ſpondere potest firm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ac ſtabile.</hi> Sen. trag. Octav. <hi>Non illa Deo vertiſſe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet quae nexa fuis currunt cauſis.</hi> Sen. <hi>in</hi> OEdip. <hi>Fatum</hi> Stoicum <hi>definit</hi> Senec. <hi>Neceſſitatem rerum omnium Deum ipſum &amp; actiones omnes huic fato ſubjicientem. vid.</hi> Lipſ. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Conſt. cap.</hi> 17. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Deſtiny</hi> the cauſe of all Alterations, which they ſay is An Event that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily falls out from a certain inevitable or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and connection of naturall Cauſes, work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without the will of God, as the ſupreme Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer and Diſpoſer of them, he being ſubjected to them, and not they to him: whereby they take away the very na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Godhead, which is to be a moſt powerfull and free Agent, that works what, and by what means it pleaſes; all ſeconda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cauſes depending upon that, and that upon none.</p>
            <p>But enough of theſe; For I muſt remember my ſelf, that I am now ſpeaking to <hi>Christians,</hi> who acknowledge the Divine Providence in all things; and therefore ſhall ſpeak no more of theſe Negative and ſuppoſed Cauſes, but ſhall now give you the true Efficient Cauſes of them by way of Affirmation.</p>
            <p>And here know that <hi>Logicians</hi> tell us of two Efficient Cauſes; Principall, and leſſe Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall: And this is twofold, Impulſive and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentall:</p>
            <p>Firſt then, the Principall Cauſe of all Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Alterations is God; for ſo ſaid the Heathen man, <note place="margin">Horat. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rm. 1. 1. Od<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 34.</note>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>—Valet ima ſummis</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:115543:20"/>
Mutare, &amp; inſignem attenuat Deus,</l>
               <l>Obſcura promens—</l>
            </lg>
            <p>But why borrow I weapons from the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtins</hi> forge, when as there is enough for this that may be drawn out of Gods Armory of the Scriptures? as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75. the 6. and 7. verſes: <hi>Promotion,</hi> ſaies the Prophet, <hi>comes neither from the Eaſt, nor from the Weſt, nor from the South; but God is the Judge, he puts down one, and ſets up another.</hi> So alſo <hi>Job</hi> 34. verſ. 29. <hi>When he gives Quietneſſe, who can make Trouble?</hi> and <hi>when he hides his face, who can behold him; whether it be done</hi> (ſaies <hi>Elihu) againſt a nation, or againſt a particular man only?</hi> Again <hi>Amos</hi> 5. 8. <hi>He makes the Seven Starres and</hi> Orion, <hi>and turnes the ſhadow of Death into the morning: The Lord is his Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Oratour expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes this well, by compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Gods omnipotency <note place="margin">
                  <hi>U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hominum membra nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la contentione mente ipſa ac voluntate moventur: Sic divino n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mine moven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ac mutantur omnia,</hi> Tully <hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>de natura Deorum.</hi>
               </note> to the power of the ſoul over the members of the body, which upon the leaſt intimation of the mind do turn and move about with all facility. Now God (ſaies he) is the ſole mind of the Univerſe, and hath all parts and parcells there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of at his b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ck and pleaſure, to be turn'd into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhape or form at his diſpoſall.</p>
            <p>Nay, it is no diſhonour for God to caſt the eye of his providence upon the alteration even of the meaneſt things: for <hi>who is like,</hi> ſayes the Pſalmiſt, <hi>to the Lord our God, who hath his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 113. ver. 5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>dwelling on high, and yet humbles himſelf to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115543:21"/>
the things in Heaven and Earth?</hi> Not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to behold the things in Heaven, which is a great condeſcenſion to him, <hi>whom the Heaven</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Reg. 8. verſ. 27.</note> 
               <hi>and the Heaven of Heavens cannot contain;</hi> but alſo the things in Earth. Now how unworthy theſe are of his taking notice of, you may ſee by thoſe diminutive expreſſions of them compared with Gods greatneſſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40. 15. where the Prophet ſaies, <hi>Behold, the Nations are but as the drop of a Bucket, and are counted as the ſmall duſt of the Ballance; Behold, he takes up the Iſles as a very little thing.</hi> And if this be not low enough for them, he ſayes further, verſe 17. That <hi>all Nations before him are as nothing, and are counted to him as leſſe then nothing.</hi> Now look what a wide difference there is betwixt the Sea and a Bucket of water, yea the Drop of a Bucket; or betwixt a heap of duſt, and the ſmall duſt of the ballance; betwixt very great and very little; betwixt all things and nothing at all, yea leſſe then nothing, (if leſſe could be:) ſo vaſt is the diſproportion betwixt God and all Nations, which are the greateſt among all earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things. And yet for all this, is God pleaſ'd ſo far<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to extenuate his own Greatneſſe, and to take off from it, as to look after them, and run them about in their ſeverall ſtages from one point unto another.</p>
            <p>And if you would have this truth to be made out further unto you, our <hi>Saviour</hi> doth it <hi>Matt.</hi> 10. 29. by two ſeverall inſtances.</p>
            <p>The one is of two Sparrows, which are lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle birds and of ſmall value; but the <hi>Greek</hi> yet runs it more diminutively, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diminutivum</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> two little ſparrows;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115543:21"/>
and ſo they muſt needs be, for they were ſold both even for a Farthing, and this is price little enough. Yet the <hi>Arabick</hi> makes it leſſe, and hath for it <hi>Phals,</hi> which is the leaſt piece of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney that can be; and accordingly expreſſes the two Mites ſpoken of <hi>Mark</hi> 12. 42. (which make both but one Farthing) by <hi>Phalſain</hi> in the duall number, as a late and learned Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitor <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Hammond <hi>in locum.</hi>
               </note> notes.</p>
            <p>The other is of the Haires upon our Heads, being a kind of Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">Our haires are things ſlighted even to a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, <hi>Ne pili facio;</hi> Eraſm. Adag. <hi>ſub loco commun. contemptus &amp; vilitatis.</hi>
               </note> belonging to our bodies, &amp; no integrall or neceſſitous part of them, (as the Heart, Hands and Feet are;) and yet he tells us that God numbers theſe, and takes ſuch a particular account of them, that not one of them falls to the ground without his diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall.</p>
            <p>In the viſion of the Wheels we read of a <note place="margin">Ezek. 1. 16.</note> wheel within a wheel. Now the wheel with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is the wheel of Gods Providence, that turns about the wheels of all outward things, be they never ſo low and mean. For as God doth not labour in doing the greateſt things, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth he diſdain, either to do or undo the leaſt; but as he <hi>made the ſmall and great,</hi> (ſaies the book of <hi>Wiſdome)</hi> ſo alſo doth he <hi>care for</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Wiſd. 6. 7.</note> 
               <hi>both alike.</hi> The Potter having power over his Clay, either to make of it a veſſel of honour or <note place="margin">Rom. 9. 21.</note> diſhonour, and being made, either to preſerve it in that form and being he hath beſtowed upon
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115543:22"/>
it, or elſe to deform and deſtroy it, ſince it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitable that every one ſhould do with his own as he pleaſes. Nay, as he ſaies of the gnat, that <hi>Nuſquam potentior natura quam in minimis;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pliny nat. Hiſt.</note> So may we ſay, that God doth no wayes ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance his Power and Wiſdome more, then in ordering of the leaſt accidents to be diſpoſed of to his Glory, and the good of his Children. And ſo much for the <hi>Principall</hi> Efficient cauſe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>leſſe Principall</hi> follows; which (as I ſaid) is either <hi>Impulſive</hi> or <hi>Inſtrumentall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Impulſive</hi> cauſe of all Changes and Alterations is the ſinne of man. This uſher'd them in at the firſt, and ſo it doth ſtill. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Adam</hi> ſinned, he injoyed a Paradiſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and uninterrupted happineſſe; but ſo ſoon as he ſins againſt God, then follows a great change preſently: For the Earth all fruitfull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <note place="margin">Gen. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6. 17.</note> now becomes barren, himſelf ſubject to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, his wife to travail and ſorrow, and both to cares and troubles, to weakneſſe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution. And ſo it is alſo with Nations and Kingdomes. If they be chang'd at any time, ſinne is the cauſe of it; and the greater their ſinne is, the greater uſually is their change. Great ſinnings are the floud-gates to let in great Alterations upon them. For it is not a bare ſinning in a Nation, (from which there is none that could ever plead exemption,) but a ſinning in ſome high meaſure, that is an in-let to Changes in the higheſt kind. Which made <hi>David</hi> ſay <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107. 34. That <hi>a fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full land is turn'd into barrenneſſe for the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe of thoſe that dwell therein,</hi> which the vulgar <hi>Latine</hi> reads <hi>Propter malitiam, i. e.</hi> for
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115543:22"/>
the <hi>malicious wickedneſſe</hi> of thoſe that dwell therein; which notes a ſin of a high nature, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch a one as is perſiſted in both againſt Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge &amp; Conſcience. And therefore it is a good ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation <note place="margin">Muſculus <hi>in locum. Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſmodi mutationes terra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum non ob id tantum fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt propterea quod homines peccant, (id quod fit toto terrarum orbe) ſed quod malitioſe.</hi>
               </note> which <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſculus</hi> hath upon the words; <q>Theſe ſtrange Alterations, ſayes he, of Nations and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, are not for the ſinning of them, (from which no Nation can be free) but for their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious ſinning. And this you may ſee further in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> 
                  <bibl>Ezek. 21.</bibl>
               </q> where we read of a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great Judgement that ſhould befall her from the <hi>Babylonian, viz.</hi> Utter Deſtruction, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the threefold Overturn wherewith God threatens her verſ. 27. And verſ. 24. he laies down the Impulſive cauſe that mov'd him to it; and this is an impudent and ſhameleſſe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning againſt God: for they did not commit their ſinne in a corner, as thoſe that were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd of it, but (brazen-faced Wretches as they were) they declar'd their ſinne as <hi>Sodom,</hi> and diſcover'd it openly in the face of the ſun: and this they did too not only in one or two particular acts, but generally, ſays the Text, in all their doings.</p>
            <p>Now there is ſome hope of a modeſt and baſhfull, but none at all of a ſhameleſſe and obdurate Sinner. Thus the Father, when his Sonne hath done amiſſe, yet is he well perſwaded <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Erubuit, ſalva res eſt.</hi> Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, in Heautont.</note> of his amendment, if he
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115543:23"/>
but ſee him once bluſh upon his reproving of him. But when like <hi>Judah,</hi> he hath once a whores forehead, and refuſes to be aſhamed, then doth <note place="margin">Jer. 3. 3.</note> he give him over as a loſt child, and not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd.</p>
            <p>So that from hence we ſee, that in what place ſoever we find ſuch a Turn, ſuch an Everſion as this, where all is turn'd upſide down) there hath been without queſtion ſome great <hi>A verſio a Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atore ad Creaturam,</hi> ſome great ſinning againſt God (as the Schoolmen call it.) Which was the reaſon that when the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were (now upon their quitting of <hi>France,</hi> in <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixth's dayes) demanded of the <note place="margin">Heilens <hi>Geogr. in deſcript. of</hi> France.</note> 
               <hi>French</hi> by way of deriſion, when they would make their return thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; it was feelingly anſwered by one of our nation thus, <hi>When your ſinnes are greater then ours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is ſinne then that ruines particular Perſons, that ſubverts Families, that periods Kingdomes, that wheels about Governments, that overturns States, that disjoints Common weales, and ſayes unto them as to the proud waves, <hi>Thus farre ye ſhall go, and no further.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Job 38. 11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I have done with the Impulſive Cauſe, and come next to the Inſtrumentall cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or means which God uſes in effecting his Changes here; and they are two.</p>
            <p>The firſt is the Motion and Influences of the Celeſtiall Bodies.</p>
            <p>And this will the better appear, if we conſider their forcible workings upon the Mind of man. For though they cannot work immediately upon it, becauſe it is immateriall; yet may
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115543:23"/>
they, and do work mediately upon it, as by the Body, which is the Inſtrument of the Soul to work by, and the Caſe wherein it is put up here for a time; and ſo make it either well or ill affected, according to the Bodies preſent temper. By which means it comes to paſſe many times, that not only the diſpoſitions of particular men, but alſo of whole multitudes collected together in a politick body, are much alter'd and chang'd, either to Labour or Sloth, to Peace or Diſquiet, to good or evill actings, according as they are inclin'd by the motions of the Heavenly Bodies.</p>
            <p>And that theſe Celeſtiall Bodies have their energy upon all Sublunary things, is plain,</p>
            <p>Firſt, by Scripture; as <hi>Job</hi> 38. 33. where the Lord ſpeaks thus to <hi>Job, Know'ſt thou the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Heaven? and canſt thou ſet the dominion thereof in the Earth?</hi> which implies,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Heavens have power and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in the Earth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That this power of theirs is ſet them from <note place="margin">Astra regunt bomines, ſed regit Astra Deus.</note> Gods ordinance and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by the conſtant Obſervation and Experience of all Ages. <hi>Bodinus</hi> the <hi>French</hi> 
               <note place="margin">In lib. 4. de Rep. cap. 2.</note> Lawyer ſpeaks well to this point; Many erre (ſayes he) greatly, who think the influence of the Celeſtiall Spheres to be nothing, whenas their ſtrength hath ever been moſt effectual, as in Sacred Writ is to be ſeen: &amp; he cites the 38. chap. of <hi>Job</hi> before mentioned to prove the ſame. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding further, that many ancient Writers have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the great changes in Cities &amp; Kingdomes upon
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115543:24"/>
the conjunction of the ſuperiour Planets, but to them only where they have been deputed of God to that end and purpoſe. And that they have been inſtrumentall towards the working of ſuch effects, he ſhewes by an induction of ſome particular inſtances; As that before the tranſlation of the <hi>Roman</hi> Soveraignty unto <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> there was a great conjunction of the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour Planets met together in <hi>Scorpio:</hi> which fell out again ſeven hundred yeares after, when the <hi>Arabian</hi> Legions receiv'd the law of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet,</hi> rebell'd againſt the <hi>Greek</hi> Emperours, &amp; ſubdued the Eaſtern <hi>Aſia</hi> from the <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame alſo came about again <hi>anno Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti</hi> 1464. after which <hi>Ladamachus</hi> King of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>artars</hi> was by his Subjects thruſt out of the chair of Soveraignty, and <hi>Friderick</hi> the third driven out of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary</hi> by <hi>Matthias Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinus,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Qui volet, in codem ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite plura legal.</note> who from a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner ſtept up to the Royall Throne, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Alſtedius</hi> tells us, that the Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction <note place="margin">Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>edius <hi>(vir undequaque doctus) ait conjunctionem</hi> Saturni <hi>&amp;</hi> Jovis <hi>in Ariete (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ae triplicitatis ſigno) Anno Christi</hi> 1641. <hi>novi a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licujus imperii revolutionem portendere 3 cujus effectum verifimile eſt, nos in nuperis ab eo tempore mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ibus &amp; mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ationibus in</hi> Anglia <hi>nostra, ſatis ſuper<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vidiſſe, necdum videmus terminari.</hi> Nunt. prophetic. <hi>pag.</hi> 34.</note> of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> in February 1642. did foretell and portend the revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſome new Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire and Government to fall out after it in <hi>Europe.</hi> The effect whereof in part (its like) we have ſeen in this nation alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115543:24"/>
and may live (if God ſo diſpoſe of us) to ſee further of it yet in time to come.</p>
            <p>But to paſſe this, and to come to that daily and uſuall courſe of Gods proceedings with us in the world. Here methinks there ſhould be few, (though of ordinary capacities among us) but (if we be a little obſerving) may ſee this truth made good by the eye of our own expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, which tells us that the earth is either fruitfull or barren, and the air either wholſome or infectious, ſuitably to that meaſure and manner of influence they receive from them.</p>
            <p>And therefore when God will at any time bring about ſome great change in the world, it is then eaſy to ſee how uſually he fits his inferiour means, according to their ſeverall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, for the orderly tranſacting of it in thoſe ſtations wherein he hath ſet them. As when he will turn a fruitfull land into barrenneſſe, and again, a barren land into fruitfulneſſe, (which he promiſ'd his own people, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2. 21.) there he tells them in what order he will work it; <hi>I will hear</hi> (ſays he) <hi>the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and they ſhall hear the Earth, and they ſhall hear</hi> Jezreel. For this is a ſure rule, That the ſupreme cauſe of all doth not take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the natures and workings of ſecondary cauſes, but rather eſtabliſh them: which is the reaſon of that ſpeech of God to <hi>Job</hi> in the ordinary revolution of the times and ſeaſons of the year, <hi>Job</hi> 38. 31. <hi>Canſt thou bind the ſweet influences of the</hi> Pleiades, <hi>and looſe the bonds of</hi> Orion?</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Pleiades</hi> are thoſe we commonly call the Seven Starres, that have their influence
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115543:25"/>
on the earth by producing ſweet ſhowres to the opening and refreſhing of it, about the Spring of the year, and <hi>Orion</hi> is a Conſtellation moſt conſpicuous in the Winter ſeaſon, as having a commiſſionary power to bind up the earth with Froſts. Again, <hi>canſt thou bring forth</hi> Mazza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roth <hi>in his ſeaſon; i. e.</hi> the twelve Signes ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quid de his ſtellis ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us dicant Astronomi, non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt hic noſtrum tractare ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curatius: tantum dicemus id quod locus hic poſtulat, non ab alio quam Dev vim illam stellis pluviam &amp; frigus generandi datam.</hi> Sanct. in Job.</note> after one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;) <hi>or guide</hi> Arctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus <hi>with his Sons? (i. e.</hi> the Polar ſtarre, as ſome will have it, with thoſe <hi>ignes minores</hi> that wait upon him; or <hi>Bootes,</hi> as others. It is not then ſo much the Earth, as the Heavens that give us either fruit, or withhold it; they being the firſt ordinary means, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by God uſes to work out alterations in ſubluna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry things.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Inſtrumentall cauſe of theſe ſtrange Viciſſitudes here below, is the Will of Man; For though it have not a liberty to ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, yet all grant it a liberty to externall acts, and morall goodneſſe. And this Liberty of mans will doth God uſe as an under-wheel to turn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout moſt of thoſe Alterations that are in the world.</p>
            <p>It is true, that health and ſickneſſe, peace and warre, plenty and ſcarcity, riches and poverty, proceed from God as the principall Efficient cauſe; but yet for all this we deny not but that God makes uſe both of our ſelves and others, as to the means of bringing them about. The life
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115543:25"/>
of <hi>Joſeph</hi> was checquer'd with variety of acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents; for he is now a Slave to the <hi>Iſmaelites,</hi> and by and by a Prince in <hi>Aegypt.</hi> Now theſe although they proceeded from God as the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour, yet was the will of his Brethren, as the will of <hi>Reuben</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> the inſtruments of <note place="margin">Gen. c. 37.</note> preſerving his life, and the wills of his other Brethren the meanes of ſelling him into <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now becauſe it is the Nature of Inſtruments <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Inſtrumentum niſi à prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipali Agente motum, non operatur,</hi> Aquin. 3. <hi>part. Summae quaest.</hi> 62. <hi>Art.</hi> 4.</note> to be ſubſervient to the Principall Agent, and to be determin'd by it; therefore give me leave here by the way to faſten this exhortation upon you, That in all Changes whatſoever you will look beyond the Inſtruments of them, unto God the Principall Agent. For ſo did <hi>Job</hi> in his loſſes, beyond the plundring <hi>Chaldeans</hi> and <hi>Sabeans,</hi> unto <hi>Dominus abſtulit, The Lord hath given, and the Lord hath taken away;</hi> looking <note place="margin">Job 1. 21.</note> upon them as we uſe to do upon an <hi>Index, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum in ordine ad Librum,</hi> only in order to the Book it ſelf, <hi>et in tranſitu ad Deum,</hi> in his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage unto God, who ſets them awork, as to their naturall powers and faculties, though to the evill of them no otherwiſe, then by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering and over-ruling it to the good of his Children. And hence it is that the wicked are call'd Gods Sword, as in the 17 <hi>Pſalm</hi> verſe 13. <hi>Deliver my ſoul</hi> (ſaies <hi>David) from the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked which is thy Sword.</hi> And ſo muſt we in all thoſe Loſſes that befall us here, have in our eye not ſo much the Sword, as the Hand that holds
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115543:26"/>
it; which will be one means, and a good one too, to bring us to <hi>Davids</hi> calm temper in the 39. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. who ſaies in the like condition, That <hi>he was dumb, and did not open his mouth,</hi> nor let fall an impatient word in it, becauſe it was Gods doing: And therefore when <hi>Abiſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> would have taken a way <hi>Shime<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'s</hi> life for curſing of <hi>David,</hi> No, (ſayes he) <hi>Let him alone, Juſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> enim Dominus, for the Lord hath bidden him curſe; who then</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 16. 11.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall ſay, Wherefore haſt thou done ſo? q. d.</hi> Who then dare expoſtulate with God, or call him to account about it, as if he were unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in it; ſince evill men are but Swords in Gods hand, who, when he hath once done his work by them, will either put them up again into his Scabbard, and lay them by, or elſe ſo blunt the edge of their power, that it ſhall not cut, or elſe break them a pieces, and throw them quite away? And ſo much for the Efficient Cauſes of Viciſſitudes.</p>
            <p>Next I ſhall ſpeak to the Ends, or Finall Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of them. <note place="margin">4</note>
            </p>
            <p>And theſe are either <hi>Ex parte Dei,</hi> or <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri;</hi> In reſpect of God, or our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Firſt, In reſpect of God; and ſo the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall End why God rings ſuch Changes upon all earthly things, and will have them diſpoſed of after ſo various a manner, is to make them by it the more tunable to his own Glory, which by this meanes is exceedingly magnify'd, and advanc'd: but eſpecially in the Attributes of his Power, Truth, Wiſdome and Goodneſſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In his Power and Omnipotency: that ſo he may let the world know, that the Finger of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115543:26"/>
his Power is in all tranſactions; and that he can do whatſoever he will, both in heaven and earth, and yet changes not.</p>
            <p>For why elſe did God work ſo many mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Changes in <hi>Aegypt</hi> by the hand of <hi>Moſes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why turn'd he <hi>Moſes</hi> Rod into a Serpent, and the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Waters into Bloud?</p>
            <p>Why their Duſt into Lice and Flies, and their Light into Darkneſſe for the ſpace of three dayes together?</p>
            <p>Why elſe created he a new generation of Frogs and Locuſts among them?</p>
            <p>Why unheard of diſeaſes upon themſelves and upon their cattell?</p>
            <p>Why deſtroyed he their Herbs and Fruit-trees with Hail, and their Firſt-born with untimely death?</p>
            <p>In a word, Why cauſ'd he the Red-ſea to go out of its naturall courſe and chanell, whereby it became a wall to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and a grave to the <hi>Aegyptians?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Did not God all this to make known the glory of his power, in the preſervation of the one and deſtruction of the other? Yes; <hi>For this</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exod. 9. 16.</note> 
               <hi>cauſe</hi> (ſayes God to <hi>Moſes) I have raiſed thee up, to ſhew in thee my power, and that my name may be declared in all the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He advances alſo his Glory this way, by manifeſting his Truth and Faithfulneſs: in that thoſe things which are accidentall in regard of us, and ſeem as impoſſible, yet are they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly brought to paſſe in their due times and ſeaſons. As in the bringing of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> wherein God was full as good as his
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115543:27"/>
word, and kept touch with them to a day in their Deliverance; as you may ſee <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. 41. where we read, That <hi>it came to paſſe in the end of four hundred and thirty years, even the ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame day it came to paſſe, that all the hoſts of the Lord went out of the land of Aegypt.</hi> All <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> oppoſitions and tergiverſations could not prorogue their Bondage ſo much as one day beyond the time prefix'd of God, but ſerv'd only to fill up that <hi>Interim,</hi> or void ſpace of time betwixt Gods Promiſe made to <hi>Abraham</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 15. 13.</note> and his performance of it.</p>
            <p>And if you ask by what intervalls of time the truth of this promiſe came about ſo punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide nuperrimas Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationes in Gen.</hi> 15. 13.</note> Divines will tell you, That from <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham's</hi> receiving of the promiſe, unto the birth of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> were five and twenty years; ſixty from thence to <hi>Jacobs</hi> birth; and to his death (which fell out preſently upon their entrance into <hi>Aegypt)</hi> a hundred and thirty yeares. After which unto the death of <hi>Levi,</hi> who was <hi>Ultimus Patriarcharum,</hi> the laſt of the Patriarchs that ſurvived, and in which ſpace the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were kindly entreated for <hi>Joſeph's</hi> ſake, were ninety four years; and a hundred and one and twenty more of cruell Bondage, untill <hi>Moſes</hi> came to deliver them from it in the reign of <hi>Pharaoh Cencres.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which particulars being gathered up to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, do make up the complete ſumme of four hundred and thirty yeares, and may ſerve to juſtify God in all his ſayings, and to clear his truth in the leaſt circumſtance and pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctilio
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115543:27"/>
of time, when it ſhall come to be judged.</p>
            <p>For when once Gods appointed time is come to introduce a change, either for better or worſe, among any people, then ſhall eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry breath of wind, how croſſe ſoever it ſeems to blow at the preſent, yet be ſo farre from hindering Gods work in it, as that one way or other you ſhall find it in the ſequel, to contribute its help and aſſiſtance to it.</p>
            <p>3. God advances alſo his Glory this way, in the manifeſtation of his Wiſdome and Goodneſſe; in that he makes a ſweet har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of ſo many different cords and chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and frames a moſt admirable Order out of a ſeeming Diſorder and Confuſion.</p>
            <p>Many and diverſe are the qualities of Herbs, yet if a skilfull Simpler hath the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them, he knows how to make of them a well-reliſh'd and wholſome Sallade: So, many were the interchangeable paſſages that happen'd to <hi>Joſeph;</hi> and had we the ſame, it may be we ſhould think them very confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ones; but yet let the Wiſdome and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God but lay them together, and we ſhall preſently find, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> did, the cloſe of them all in a ſweet <hi>diapaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For though all things, as to us, are float<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up and down, to and again, by chance as it were and accident; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>G.</hi> Nazian. <hi>in Invect. in</hi> Julianum.</note> ſayes <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory Nazianzen;</hi> yet if we look to the order and appointment of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115543:28"/>
Gods Providence, (which doth alwayes moſt wiſely contrive all events for the good of his Children,) they are fixt and ſtable, howbeit they may ſeem to go contrary at the preſent.</p>
            <p>And of Gods dealing in this kind we have <hi>Job</hi> an eminent example; who is to day the greateſt man for Wealth and Honour in all the Eaſt, (and a tablet of this his Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe you may ſee in his nine and twentieth chapter, which I deſire you to read over at your leiſure,) wherein you ſhall find a whole <hi>ſeries</hi> of worldly Proſperity to wait upon him;) yet to morrow he is poor, even to a by-word and proverb, <hi>As poor as</hi> Job: inſomuch as he ſpends all the next chapter in <note place="margin">Chap. 30.</note> bemoaning his ſuddain change, beginning it with a <hi>But;</hi> which though a ſmall monoſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable, yet as the Helme of a Ship turns a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the veſſel any way, ſo doth this <hi>But</hi> turn about <hi>Job</hi> and all his former Honour and Proſperity, into the extremeſt contempt and adverſity. <hi>But now,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>they that are younger then I have me in deriſion, whoſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Job 30. verſe 1.</note> 
               <hi>fathers I would have diſdained to have ſet with the dogs of my Flock;</hi> and ending it with this dolefull accent, verſe laſt, <hi>verſa eſt cithara mea in luctum, &amp; organum in vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem flentium; My harp is turned into mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and my organ into the voice of thoſe that weep.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet all is well (we ſay) that ends well; and ſo it was with <hi>Job,</hi> which makes Saint <hi>James</hi> ſay by way of ſupport unto Gods
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:115543:28"/>
people in their afflictions, <hi>Ye have heard of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">James 5. 11.</note> 
               <hi>the patience of</hi> Job, <hi>and have ſeen the end of the Lord; i. e.</hi> what good end God gave him in it; for the next day God brings a great deal of Light out of this Darkneſſe, by a wiſe and gracious diſpoſing of all that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill to him for the beſt, in giving him twice <note place="margin">Job laſt, verſe 12.</note> as much as he had at the firſt, and bleſſing his later end more then his beginning.</p>
            <p>So that although for a time all thoſe ſad Changes that befell <hi>Job,</hi> ſeem'd even to croſſe the ordinary courſe of Gods care and Providence to him; yet in the concluſion you ſee how his Wiſedome and Goodneſſe cut them all out, and made them ſerve to his greater Honour and Abundance.</p>
            <p>And ſo much for the Ends or Finall Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in reſpect of God.</p>
            <p>They follow now in reſpect of ourſelves.</p>
            <p>And theſe are two: firſt to confirm our Faith; ſecondly to reform our lives, and to work out by them good to his ſervants.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to confirm our Faith.</p>
            <p>And ſo God brings many times great Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges into the world, to try, if amidſt thoſe ſhakings of outward things among us, we will be ſhaken in our Faith, or not. That as the Apoſtle ſpeakes of hereſies 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 19. <hi>Oportet eſſe Hoereſes, There must be He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies among you, that they which are appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved may be made manifeſt;</hi> ſo ſay I, <hi>Oportet eſſe mutationes,</hi> There muſt be Changes: and theſe not ſo much in reſpect of the things themſelves, which are in their own natures
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115543:29"/>
liable to alteration and diſſolution; as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Gods end in it, that they which are approved and ſincere in the faith, may be manifeſted to be ſo, by their conſtancy and perſeverance in it. That as there is a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Fire to try Gold, whether it be true or elſe counterfeit; ſo alſo is there a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Changes: for by theſe it will appear, whether we will meaſure our Religion by outward things, and in the loſſe or enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them be loſt in our Proteſtant Faith, yea or no.</p>
            <p>There is nothing, Beloved, more diſcovers the Hypocrite then his <hi>Ingenium verſatile,</hi> (as <hi>Livy</hi> ſaid of <hi>Cato)</hi> then his turning hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour in Religion: for which I do not ſay he ſhall be plagued in <note place="margin">Plutarch <hi>ſeigns</hi> Theſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius <hi>returning from Hell, and telling (among other things he ſaw there infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted on evill men) that hypocrites were there pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by turning up and down continually.</hi> Plut. <hi>Do his qui ſero puniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, pag.</hi> 203.</note> Hell, by being wheel'd about there continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without any relaxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (though that may ſeem a puniſhment ſomewhat ſuitable to his Weathercock-diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition here upon earth;) no, <hi>Hoc ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis Ethnicum,</hi> This is too heatheniſh: but rather with the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> That <hi>he ſhall turn into Hell with all thoſe that forget God.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 9. 17.</note> which is that portion of Hypocrites mention'd by our Saviour <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. laſt.</p>
            <p>For if an Apple be rotten at the coare, it will not hold long upon the Tree, but upon the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115543:29"/>
leaſt Wind will fall from it. And ſo it is with the rotten-hearted Hypocrite; if a little croſſe wind do but blow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, oh how ſoon doth he fall off from the tree of Life, and become a wind-fall in his Religion, for the Devil that old Serpent to prey upon!</p>
            <p>Every Cock-boat (you know) will bear up well enough in a calm ſea: but that is a ſtout Veſſell that can live in the moſt troubled water. And <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Cyprian <hi>de lapſis; &amp;</hi> Fox <hi>Martyr.</hi> p. 1362.</note> too too many there were in the Primitive times that, like Dr <hi>Pendleton</hi> in Queen <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> dayes, boaſted much of their Conſtancy in the Orthodox Faith during <hi>Conſtantines</hi> dayes, ſo long as God hedg'd about his Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard with Peace and Proſperity; but ſo ſoon as that Hedge was broken down, and erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous, yea hereticall Doctrines were let in <note place="margin">Pſalm 80. 12. and 13 verſes.</note> like ſo many Beaſts of prey to devoure, then how quickly did theſe prove Turncoats, and Apoſtates from the Faith!</p>
            <p>But as for the true Chriſtian, he is like a Rock—<hi>mediis immo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in undis:</hi> That al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the waves are alwaies ſwelling againſt <note place="margin">Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gil.</note> him, yet is he the ſame man ſtill in his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion, and wavers not: or elſe like that Houſe built upon the Rock, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <note place="margin">Mat 25. 7.</note> which the Flouds came, and the Winds blew, but it fell not, becauſe it was built up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Rock.</p>
            <p>And ſuch a well-built houſe was Saint <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil,</hi> who being threatned with death by <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:115543:30"/>
if he would not adviſe further and turn <hi>Arrian,</hi> anſwer'd with this brave reſolution, <q>
                  <note place="margin">Sozom. biſt. lib. 6. c. 16. <hi>In hoc mihi conſilio non est opus: nam idem qui jam ſum, cras etiam fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turus ſum.</hi>
                  </note> I need not any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther advice then I have taken already about this matter; for to morrow I ſhall be the ſame man that I am to day therein, and no other.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And here know that ſome things are of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, wherein we cannot but change, as in naturall, civill and morall things, and to change in theſe is only humane.</p>
            <p>Others again are of Duty: and theſe either prohibited, or enjoyn'd.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Prohibited; as in evill and erroneous things: and to change here is pious and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine: and not to change, either Weakneſſe or Obſtinacy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Enjoyn'd, as in ſacred and religious: and to change here is impious and Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolicall; and not to change, true Chriſtian Fortitude and Conſtancy.</p>
            <p>Whatſoever things we ſee then wheeling about in the world, as Governments, Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies and the like, nay howſoever we may change our ſelves or be chang'd in ſome things of an indifferent nature, by thoſe that have dominion over our Bodies and Eſtates; yet is there no man that hath dominion over our Faith: But this is Gods peculiar, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">2 Cor. 1. laſt.</note> in this we muſt not change.</p>
            <p>It is not with ſaving Truths as it is
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115543:30"/>
with Clothes, which alter every year as the faſhion doth: for <hi>the faſhion of the world paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes away</hi> (ſayes Saint <hi>John;)</hi> but true Religion <note place="margin">1 John 2. 17.</note> is ever in faſhion with good men and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not.</p>
            <p>And herein we may juſtly take occaſion to bewail the unſteadineſſe of ſome in theſe times, who are mere <hi>Scepticks</hi> in Religion, alwayes conceiving ſome new Opinions in it, and alwayes in pain till they be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd of their new conceptions, though never ſo <hi>monſtrous</hi> and <hi>deformed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which was truth with them yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> Magd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>burgenſes <hi>tell us</hi> Cent. 4. c. 11. <hi>that ſuch was</hi> Euſtathius <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Sebaſte, <hi>who was one day for the</hi> Homouſian, <hi>and another for the</hi> Homoiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian <hi>Confeſſion, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly as they ſuited best with his preſent turn.</hi>
               </note> is no ſuch thing to day; and what is ſo to day is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to morrow; ſuch Changelings there be in this laſt Age, who like the Moon do ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver appear the ſame two dayes together! <q>And I would to God, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Atque utinam vel ſic mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentur: Hoec enim cito ad plen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>udinem ſuam redit, hi vero nec ſero conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuntur.</hi> Ambroſ. <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riis actionibus</hi> conc. 4. <hi>in</hi> Tom. 5.</note> ſayes Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> that their change were no worſe then that of the Moon; for ſhe returns a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain within a little time to her full light, but theſe never.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And he is blind that ſees not this among us, (namely) how ſome turn every day to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:115543:31"/>
               <hi>Popiſh</hi> Superſtition, but more to <hi>Anabaptiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> Francies; ſome unto <hi>Socinian</hi> Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, but moſt unto <hi>Atheiſticall</hi> Notions, and all into Senſuality; this being the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Sewer into which all the former run, and are ultimately reſolved.</p>
            <p>But as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to his <hi>Galathians,</hi> ſo do I to ſuch, <hi>O fooliſh</hi> Galathians, <hi>who hath</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Galat. 3. 1.</note> 
               <hi>bewitch'd you that you ſhould not obey the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel?</hi> And it is a metaphor, ſayes one, from Sorcerers, who uſe to caſt a miſt before the peoples eyes, that ſo they may not take a right view of what is preſented to them: As if he had ſaid, Who hath caſt a miſt before the eyes of your underſtandings, to make that appear unto you for truth which indeed is not? What? <hi>Are ye ſo fooliſh, that having begun in the ſpirit, ye will be perfected in the fleſh?</hi> So, Are ye ſo fooliſh, that having begun in truth, ye will end in falſhood? or can ye be ſo ſimple, as to exchange Gold for Dirt, Wheat for Chaffe, and your pretious Faith, as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> calls it, which is the ſubſtance <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 1. Heb. 11. 1.</note> of things hoped for, for Errours of all ſorts, and mere ſhadows of Truth? I trow not. For if Errour (as our <hi>Kingly Divine</hi> ſaid well) have any <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, pag. 137.</note> advantage, it conſiſts in No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty: or if Truth any, it conſiſts in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy.</p>
            <p>Was the Doctrine then of the Reformed Churches, and the Harmony of our Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions grounded upon evident and pregnant
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:115543:31"/>
Scriptures, maintain'd by the Orthodox and primitive Fathers, and conveyed to us by the conſtant tradition of the univerſall Church, the Faith of Chriſt once deliver'd to the Saints, and the Truth of God yeſterday? why, ſo it is to day, and will be to morrow alſo. And therefore to day in our profeſſion of it we muſt be as yeſterday, and to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row as this day: becauſe as God is the ſame <note place="margin">Heb. 13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> yeſterday, to day, and for ever; ſo alſo is the Truth of God, That which was once ſo, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Veritas Dei una ſemper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſui ſimilis: In prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat. ad</hi> Harm. Confeſ.</note> will be ſo alwayes, and cannot be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
            <p>Oh that we would then be exhorted in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> words, To <hi>ſtand faſt in the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Faith, to quit our ſelves like men, and be ſtrong: and not to be as children, toſs'd to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phora a rota, quae motu continuo circumacta par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſummas &amp; imas ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per commutat,</hi> Pareus in locum.</note> 
               <hi>and fro, and carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with every wind</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 20.</note> 
               <hi>of Doctrine; but to be as men in underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſtedfast and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable;</hi> that ſo God may have cauſe to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on our behalf, as he did on <hi>Jobs, Haſt thou conſider'd</hi> (ſayes God to Sathan) <hi>my ſervant</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Job 2. 3.</note> Job? So, haſt thou conſider'd ſuch a ſervant of mine? Seeſt thou to how many changes I have ſubjected him? to changes in his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, to changes in his Eſtate, to changes in his Liberty, to changes in his Friends and Acquaintance? Nay, ſeeſt thou how many
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:115543:32"/>
of his Brethren are chang'd of late, from a fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briſh diſtemper before, now into a ſleepy le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chargy? Seeſt thou how indifferent they are for their religion round about him, and how many ſhaken reeds there are on every ſide <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nec iratum colere desti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>men.</hi> Sen. <hi>ad</hi> Marc. cap. 13.</note> of him? And yet for all this, as my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant <hi>Job</hi> did, ſo doth he ſtill hold his integrity. But enough of this.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Gods end alſo in it is, To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form our lives, and do us good by his ſo va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious diſpenſations to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us. Hence we <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Huic affine eſt illud</hi> Amos 9. v. 9. <hi>ubi duo conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randa; vel purgatum frumentum à ſordibus, vel exagitatum à cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brante, dum ab uno cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bri laterc in alterum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellitur.</hi> Sanct. <hi>in locum.</hi>
               </note> read <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30. 28. of a ſieve of vanity, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God ſayes he will ſift the Nations, and ſhake them to and fro one after another, that ſo he may winnow them from that Chaffe of ſinne that is within them. For why was <hi>Moab at eaſe from his youth?</hi> why <hi>ſettled he upon his lees,</hi> and held ſtill his <hi>corrupt taſte?</hi> but becauſe he was never diſquieted, nor <hi>emptied from veſſel to veſſel,</hi> Jer. 48. 11. Thus a ſedentary life we find very ſubject to Diſeaſes; and a long ſtanding Proſperity to a Nation, is like a ſtanding Pool, whoſe water doth ſoon puddle and putrify. And this is the reaſon of that ſpeech of <hi>David</hi> Pſal. 55. 19. <hi>Becauſe they have no Changes therefore they fear not God;</hi> making by it the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:115543:32"/>
uncheckt proſperity of worldly men a great occaſion of their continuance in ſinne, and ſo an <hi>Index</hi> of Gods Wrath upon them, rather then of his ſpeciall Favour to them.</p>
            <p>And therefore now we have ſeen the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of God moving the waters of this Church and State by inteſtine Warre, new Opinions in Religion, by Sects, diviſions and the like; it will be good for us to meditate, how God hereby intends to purge us from that ſinfull filth that adheres to us as our diſreſpect to Gods Miniſters, and contempt of his Word, our Cruelty and Oppreſſion, our Pride and Security, our Worldly-mindedneſſe and Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie.</p>
            <p>Indeed men, who are the inſtruments of them, may have other ends in ſuch Alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as to wreak their own ſpleen upon their adverſaries, to unhorſe others, and get them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the ſaddle either of Profit or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment; (That as <hi>Demetrius</hi> the Silver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith ſaid, <hi>We get our gaines by this means;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 19. 25.</note> ſo ſay they, We get our Honours and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates by theſe means, for if the waters had not been troubled, we had catch'd nothing;) or elſe to ſatisfy their own corrupt wills and pleaſures; as the Authour to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> ſayes of earthly parents, That they chaſten their children after their own pleaſure, but <note place="margin">Hebrews 12. 10.</note> God who is the ſupreme Agent, he doth it for our profit, and not his own; there being no ends of gold and ſilver, no mere will or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge in his end, but only our profit, and to take away the droſſe from the ſilver, that <note place="margin">Prov. 25. 4.</note>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:115543:33"/>
ſo he may bring forth (to uſe <hi>Solomon</hi>'s expreſſion) a <hi>Vas electum</hi> a choſen Veſſel, <note place="margin">Prov. 25. 4. Acts 9. 15.</note> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> was, and fit for the Finer.</p>
            <p>Thus the Scripture tells us of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> how he was paſs'd over from his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to the <hi>Iſmaelites,</hi> and from them to <hi>Potiphar;</hi> and his brethren had one end in it, but God another: for they did it for evil againſt him, (as he tells them himſelf,) <note place="margin">Gen. laſt, ver. 20.</note> and to get twenty Pieces by the ſale of him; but as for God, he meant it to him for good, and to ſave much people alive.</p>
            <p>And ſo alſo was <hi>Chriſt</hi> the Antitype of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> thruſt (as we ſay) from poſt to pillar, <hi>viz.</hi> from <hi>Judas</hi> to <hi>Caiaphas,</hi> from him to <hi>Pilate,</hi> from <hi>Pilate</hi> to <hi>Herod,</hi> from <hi>Herod</hi> back again to <hi>Pilate,</hi> and then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of the clamorous and unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable multitude to be crucified: and <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> had one end in <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s death, but God another. The end of <hi>Judas</hi> in it was to ſilver his bagge with thirty Pieces, but Gods end was to ſatisfy his own Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, <note place="margin">Mat 26. 9.</note> and to ſave mankind by it.</p>
            <p>So that let mens ſinfull ends in theſe Changes and Alterations be what they will, yet is Gods end in it the gaining of glory to himſelf, by his taking away that ſinne and corruption which he ſees contracted in us by a long ſtanding ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:115543:33"/>
And if theſe changes of his be not as a gentle fire to purify us, they ſhall be as a conſuming fire to deſtroy us.</p>
            <p>And ſo much for the Efficient and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall cauſes of Viciſſitudes.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Uſes</hi> follow; And they are three.</p>
            <p>Firſt, To take us off from our greedy deſire of worldly things.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To unpride us in a proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous condition.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, To comfort and ſupport us in an afflicted one.</p>
            <p>And to this purpoſe there is a good ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Marcus Aurelius Antoninus</hi> the beſt of all the Heathen Emperours, which is this,</p>
            <p>
               <q>Meditate (ſayes he) with thy ſelf how ſwiftly all things that ſubſiſt are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried a way: for both <note place="margin">
                     <hi>In his Meditat. tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by</hi> Merric Caſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon <hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 19.</note> the ſubſtances them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall flux, and all actions in a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall change, yea the cauſes of them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſubject to a thouſand alterations, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any thing that can be ſaid to be ſettled or at a ſtand.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>And from hence he draws this inference:
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:115543:34"/>
Art thou not then unwiſe, who for theſe things art either diſtracted with cares, puff'd up too much with pride, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected with troubles?</q>
            </p>
            <p>And it may put many of us Chriſtians to the bluſh, who ſeldome make ſo good <note place="margin">
                  <hi>uſe</hi> 1.</note> uſe of it as this Heathen did, though we have a farre clearer light then he had to guide us to it.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of this point, <hi>viz.</hi> The great Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſitude <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Brevi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> est &amp; caduca hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus ſeculi gloria: igitur deſpice tranſitoria, ut habeas aeterna.</hi> Bern. <hi>lib. de mod. vivend. Serm.</hi> 8.</note> and Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy of all earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, may ſerve to wean our hearts from the pleaſing teat of this World, and to raiſe them up to that place where on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fixed good is found.</p>
            <p>Here we are all too apt with the rich fool to ſet down our reſts, when (God knows) we have little or no cauſe ſo to do. <hi>Neſcis enim, ah neſcis ſerus quid veſper ferat;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Horat.</note> Since we do not know what the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y of this evening, nay leſſe of this hour, or moment may help to bring forth.</p>
            <p>It may be a change of our Eſtates in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Beggery by Fire, Thieves, and the like; or elſe of our Liberty into Thraldome; or
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:115543:34"/>
of our Health into Sickneſſe; all theſe ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively wheeling about, untill at laſt our great change come from Life to Death, and ſwallow up the reſt, as the ſea doth the waters that fall into it.</p>
            <p>Alas! here we are ſubject to a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand caſualties; but in Heaven, there, there we ſhall meet with no ſuch altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; for that is a <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, A Kingdome that is not floating up and down, as earthly Kingdomes are in the ſea of this world with every tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt.</note> Kingdome that cannot be ſhaken as earthly <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 28.</note> Kingdomes are, either by warre, factions, all-eating time, or the like. No; but there is Peace without War, Quiet without Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Freedome without Thraldome, Day without Night, Health without Sickneſſe, and Life without Death: whereas here it is farre otherwiſe; for God takes away one it may be, with <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hunc necat febribus, illum opprimit doloribus; hunc flammis, illum gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio, &amp;c.</hi> Auguſtin. <hi>in</hi> 2 <hi>Soliloq.</hi>
               </note> a Fever, another with the Sword, as S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> reckons them up. Nay, <hi>he cuts off the ſpirits of Princes</hi> (ſayes the <hi>Pſalmiſt;)</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 76. ver. 12.</note> which <hi>Junius</hi> and <hi>Tremelius</hi> tranſlate by <hi>Vindemiat. i. e.</hi> he ſlips them off as a Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tager doth a Bunch of Grapes from a
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:115543:35"/>
Tree, it is ſo quickly done. Even the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt enterprizes that the greateſt Magnifico's of the earth undertake, God doth but blow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon them a little with the breath of his diſpleaſure, and how ſoon are they bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted and ſhrink away to nothing!</p>
            <p>An example of this we have in <hi>Xcrxes,</hi> who went againſt <note place="margin">Juſtin. hiſt. lib. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Greece</hi> with a million of men, and as many ſhips as cover'd the <hi>Hell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſpont;</hi> as if he would have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued the Sea, have put a hook into her jaws, and have led her away in triumph: yet how ſoon was his over-bold pride daſh'd in pieces by a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quem dies vidit veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens ſuper bum, Hunc dies vidic fugicus jacentem.</hi> Sen. <hi>trag. in</hi> Thyeſt. <hi>oct.</hi> 3.</note> full of Greeks! One and the ſame day ſaw him both happy and miſerable; uſing him as a tender and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent Mother in the morning, but in the evening as a cruell and hard Stepdame.</p>
            <p>Oh the folly then of thoſe that lye al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſucking at theſe earthly flowers, which are as various in their ſhapes, as ever <hi>Protens</hi> was, and conſtant in nothing ſave in their inconſtancy!</p>
            <p>It was the ſaying of <hi>Maximilian</hi> the ſecond, That every year of our life was a
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:115543:35"/>
climactericall year, and brought with it ſome great change or other.</p>
            <p>And if every year be ſo changeable, what fools then are they that joyn land to land, and houſe to houſe, that they may dwell alone in the earth! yea what mean great men to pride it ſo much in their <hi>Babels</hi> here below, and out of a greedy deſire of gain to run <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quid quod ultra limites clientium ſalis avarus, parum locuples continen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ripa?</hi> Horat. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>ode</hi> 18.</note> out of their own chanels, and to call their lands by their own names? For they that do thus, declare plainly that they think themſelves to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy a ſettled eſtate here on earth, as if <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quaſi aut nunquam eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent mutabiles, aut vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam caeleſtem non expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctarent.</hi> Bellarm. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de aetern. faelicit.</hi>
               </note> they ſhould never ſee a change, or at leaſt did not for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent look for in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a better and more enduring ſubſtance, as the Authour to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 34.</p>
            <p>And yet as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:115543:36"/>
ſo may we, <hi>Quis credidit auditui noſtro? who hath believed our report?</hi> or to <note place="margin">Iſa. 53. 1.</note> whom is this truth of God revealed? For it is ſtrange to ſee how few among us do believe this, that both in our perſons and eſtates we are ſo changeable.</p>
            <p>But <hi>this is their way,</hi> ſayes <hi>David, this is their fooliſhneſſe.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 49. 13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>For how ſoon did <hi>Galba</hi> ſtart aſide from the Empire, <hi>Degu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tacit.</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. lib. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Imperium,</hi> taſting it only, as <hi>Jonathan</hi> did the Honey with the end of his Spear! How ſoon was <hi>Haman</hi> chang'd from the Minion of the Court, to be the hang-by of the world!</p>
            <p>Again, how ſoon was <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> chang'd, even from a man to a Beaſt; and <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rod</hi> from the higheſt of men, to be meat even for the loweſt of Reptiles? And the proſperity of <hi>Richard</hi> the third <note place="margin">Sir <hi>Walt. Rawl.</hi> Pref. to the worlds hiſt. <hi>Oſtenditur tantum, non poſſidetur; &amp; dum pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet, tranſit;</hi> Sen. Epiſt. 110.</note> was ſo ſhort (ſays our incomparable hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an) that it took end ere himſelf could well look over it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:115543:36"/>
There is not any thing then that we can call conſtant here on earth; which makes the Authour to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſay, That <hi>he look'd for a City having foundations:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Bellarm. <hi>in eodem loco. Vere civitas caeleſtis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prie fundamentum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Upon which one gives us this note; That the Heavenly City can on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ſaid to have properly a Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whereas thoſe Cities that are on earth, do ſhow plainly by their daily ruines that they have no ſure foundation to reſt upon.</p>
            <p>Oh let this be a means to take off the wheels of our Affections from their eager purſuit after earthly things, and ſet them upon things above, <hi>where the moth can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not come at them, nor thieves break through</hi> 
               <note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. v. 19.</note> 
               <hi>to ſteal.</hi> And let us look to that charge of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 17. <hi>Charge thoſe that are rich in the world, that they truſt not in uncertain Riches;</hi> or rather in riches which are Uncertainty it ſelf in the abſtract; (for ſo the <hi>Greek</hi> runs it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>i. e.</hi> in the uncertainty of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:115543:37"/>
Riches.) And that we may in no wiſe doubt of this their uncertainty, the Wiſe man prefixes a note of certainty before this uncertainty, <hi>Certainly,</hi> (ſays he) <hi>Riches make themſelves wings, and fly away as</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 23. 5.</note> 
               <hi>an Eagle towards heaven:</hi> as if he ſhould have ſaid, Certainly Riches, and all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things are as uncertain as a Bird that is upon the wing: and therefore we muſt <note place="margin">Pſal. 62. 10.</note> not <hi>ſet our hearts upon them;</hi> but our dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prayer and practice muſt be, <hi>So to paſſe through things temporall, that ſo we do</hi> 
               <note place="margin">4 Coll. poſt Trin.</note> 
               <hi>not looſe thoſe things that are eternall:</hi> or elſe with <hi>David</hi> let us beſeech God to <hi>incline our hearts unto his Teſtimonies, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 36.</note> 
               <hi>not to Covetouſneſſe.</hi> Now this inclining our hearts unto Gods Teſtimonies, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but that holy and penitentiall change of heart and life, or elſe that turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto God with all our hearts, which God calls for at our hands, and expects from us in all his changes, whether per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall or elſe nationall. which if he find in us, then let what changes ſoever fall, they ſhall all work together for our good: but if not, we muſt then look to be as a
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:115543:37"/>
rowling ſtone, and to have our daily turns and changes in this life from one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of miſery to another, untill at laſt we turn into Hell, as <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>with all thoſe that forget God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of this point <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Uſe</hi> 2.</note> may be a good an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidote <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nemo confidat nimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſecundis, rotat o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ne fatum,</hi> Sen. <hi>Thyest. trag.</hi> 2.</note> againſt Pride in a proſperous Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſince God hath ſo ordered the Web of our lives, as that Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity as well as Proſperity is interwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in it: For there is nothing that ſwels us up ſo much as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpering <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heu CaeCae mentes cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mefactaque corda ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundis.</hi> Silius 1.</note> here in world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things; and nothing again that is more effectuall to aſſwage this ſwelling in us, then to conſider the brevity and mutability it is ſubject to.</p>
            <p>Now it ſwells us up with a high opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on either of our own Goodneſſe above o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or elſe of our own Greatneſſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Our proſpering in worldly things
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:115543:38"/>
ſwels us up with a high opinion of our own Goodneſſe above others; as</p>
            <p n="1">1. It makes us think our ſelves the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly good men in Gods eye, becauſe we are proſperous in the worlds; whereas in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, this can be no certain rule to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure out any ſuch thing by, ſince the world and the proſperity of it is ſo variable and uncertain.</p>
            <p>And therefore, when at any time God ſhall water us more then others with the lower ſprings of his earthly Bleſſings, we are not therefore to have an overweening conceit of our ſelves, and our own cauſes, above others, (as if God upon this ground had tyed his ſpeciall love either to us, or them:) For you know that when God would chuſe a King for <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he choſe him not by outward and periſhing excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies, <note place="margin">1 Sam. c. 16. verſ. 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. and 10.</note> for then he would have choſen in the room of <hi>Saul, Eliab, Aminadab,</hi> or <hi>Shammah,</hi> who were the three elder bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of <hi>David,</hi> and men of goodly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages to look upon; yet God choſe none of theſe, (ſayes the Text) but <hi>David</hi> the youngeſt of them, though not ſo outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:115543:38"/>
yet in wardly glorious, being a man af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his own heart.</p>
            <p>It is the chief argument the <hi>Turks</hi> uſe at this day, to prove themſelves the only <hi>Muſſelmen,</hi> or true believers; We thrive (ſay they) and proſper in the world; for how hath our <hi>Mahometaniſme</hi> over-run all <hi>Aſia, Africk,</hi> and the greater part of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> too! And do not they among us then reaſon more like <hi>Turks</hi> then <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> who ſpeak after this manner, Come, ſee how we bear down all before us, and ride upon the backs of the poor in triumph! Thus, and thus do we proſper in the world, and do even what we liſt; and is not this an evident ſigne we are Gods children, and that the right end of the ſtaff is ours? Sure, if we were other then Gods peculiar people, he would not bleſſe us ſo much as he doth.</p>
            <p>But to theſe I anſwer, That theſe and ſuch like are only <hi>Bona Scabelli,</hi> (as Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines diſtinguiſh well out of that place of <hi>Iſaiah,)</hi> and not <hi>Bona Throni,</hi> the goods of Gods Footſtool, (but earthen ware,) <note place="margin">Iſa. 66. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:115543:39"/>
and not the good things of his Throne, which are Grace and Glory; and therefore can ſet upon us only an earthly mark for men here to take notice of us, but not any heavenly cognizance for God to look upon us, as upon his dear and elect children. For elſe it would eaſily follow, That the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choran</hi> were better then the <hi>Bible,</hi> and the <hi>Turks</hi> fancy better then our Faith of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And were there no other ſignall place of Scripture for this, then that of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>David</hi> in his 73. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> (as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed there are very <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conſule</hi> Eccleſiaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es 7. <hi>verſ.</hi> 15. <hi>See</hi> Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes <hi>chap.</hi> 8. <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. Malachy 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. <hi>and</hi> 15. Luke 16. 25. <hi>Remember how thou in thy life receivedſt thy good things,</hi> &amp;c.</note> many;) this alone (methinks) were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to impreſſe this as a truth upon us, where he ſpeaks of ſome that are not in trouble like other men, but pride compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them about as a chain, violence co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers them as a garment, their eyes ſtand out with fatneſſe, and they have more then their heart can wiſh; yet theſe
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:115543:39"/>
(ſayes he) verſ. 12. are the ungodly who proſper in the world. And the Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> makes bold to queſtion with God about it, in theſe words, <hi>Jer.</hi> 12. 1. and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. verſes: <hi>Wherefore,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>doth the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked proſper? and why are all they in wealth that rebelliouſly tranſgreſſe?</hi> and he reſts ſatisfied with this, verſ. 3. That God did by that proſperity of theirs fatten them as ſheep to the ſlaughter, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them for the day of deſtruction. And this is that proſperity of fools that the Wiſe man ſpeaks of, which will deſtroy them. <hi>Prov.</hi> 1. 32.</p>
            <p>It is not then our thriving in Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls, but in Spiritualls, that ſpeaks us and our Faith to be accepted of God.</p>
            <p>For the truth of Grace or Religion, and the goodneſſe of a mans cauſe, is not mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by the Souldiers Sword, but by the Word of God, which is the Sword of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>God Saints no man for his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">Ethnicus Deum ſic loquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem inducit: Iſti quos pro felicibus aſpicitis, fi non qua occurrunt, ſed qua la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent videritis, vere ſunt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeri; Intus enim omne poſui bonum. <hi>Sen. lib. de Provid. cap. 6.</hi>
               </note> perſonage, for his riches, for his
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:115543:40"/>
politick head-piece of contriving, and bringing about his own worldly and ſiniſter ends, or for his armes and conqueſts; for then <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Craeſus, Ahitophel</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great had been high in Gods book: but he va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lues men only by their ſpirituals, as their graces of Faith, Humility, Patience, Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Obedience, and the like: and where he finds theſe, (how unfurniſhed ſoever they are otherwiſe,) yet <hi>theſe are mine ſaith the Lord; and in that day when I ſhall make up my Jewels, I will ſpare</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Malachy 3. 17. 18.</note> 
               <hi>them, even as a Father doth his Sonne; and then ſhall ye diſcern between the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and the wicked, betwixt him that feareth God, and him that feareth him not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed God may ſometimes permit e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill to proſper in the world, but never ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of it: for ſo acknowledges the <hi>Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh</hi> Church, <hi>Lament.</hi> 3. 35. <hi>To turn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the right of a man before the face of the moſt High,</hi> or <hi>to ſubvert a man in
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:115543:40"/>
his cauſe, the Lord approves it not.</hi> And therefore to argue from Gods permiſſion to his approbation, is a groſſe <hi>Non ſequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 55. 3.</note> nay more, a laying, our iniquity on Gods back, as if he would take it well at our hands to be made a Pack-horſe at every turn to bear all our execrable bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, and were (as <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks) ſuch <note place="margin">Pſal. 50. 21.</note> a one as our ſelves, to favour evil cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or elſe to own them as his off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring.</p>
            <p>Which made <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſius</hi> the elder con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Videtis (inquit) quam proſpera navigatio à Diis immortalibus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Sacrilegis.</hi> Va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Max. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</note> Sacriledge to be no ſinne, when he had rob'd the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at <hi>Locri,</hi> becauſe the Gods ſeem'd (as it were) to ſmile up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the action, in giving them fair Winds and Weather, both in their voiage thither and return back again.</p>
            <p>But, as it was a great blaſphemy (ſayes one) <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sr</hi> Franc. Bacon <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay</hi> 3.</note> for the Devill to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonate God, when he
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:115543:41"/>
would be <hi>ſimilts Altiſſimo;</hi> ſo is it greater to make God perſonate the Devil. And yet this he doth, that makes God patronize his evil, becauſe he <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Proſperum ſcelus vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus voeatur.</hi> Sen. <hi>trag. in</hi> He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. <hi>fur.</hi>
               </note> proſpers in it; for this brings in God ſaying, That he will be like the Prince of Darkneſſe, and makes the Holy Ghoſt to leave his Dove-like ſhape, and come only to us in the form of a greedy Raven or Vultur.</p>
            <p>2. As our proſpering in worldly things ſwells us up too high with an opinion of our own Goodneſſe, and makes us think better of our ſelves then is meet; ſo alſo doth it on the other ſide lift us up too farre with thoughts of evil towards our brethren, and make us think worſe of them, and the wayes of God they walk in, then we ſhould, by char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them as utterly deſerted of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Adverſoeres etiam ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> detrectant.</hi> Saluſt.</note> we ſee not now the ſame hedge of Gods favour about them as heretofore we
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:115543:41"/>
did, but the ſtakes that then prop'd them up, are now thrown away as uſeleſſe and unſerviceable. Whereas Afflictions on this hand are every way as temporary and tranſient, as Proſperity was on the other; and being ſo, muſt needs be as a broken reed, or a reed of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> wherewith we cannot exactly meaſure Gods Temple, nor the ſpirituall eſtate of his Children.</p>
            <p>It was a hard ſtumbling-block to the Prophet <hi>David</hi> for a time, when he ſayes that his <hi>feet were almoſt gone, and his foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ver. 2.</note> 
               <hi>had well-nigh ſlipt,</hi> upon his ſight of the wickeds proſperity; untill he went in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Sanctuary of Gods Word, where he learnt to ſettle his wavering and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſtfull thoughts: for there he ſaw that notwithſtanding his outward afflictions, that God held him up under that ſore temptation with his right hand, and would <note place="margin">ver. 23.</note> (in oppoſition to tranſitory goods, which are the proper bleſſings of the wicked, becauſe they have no others but theſe to truſt unto) guide him with that which ſhould infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely exceed them, to wit, his Counſell ere, and his Glory hereafter.</p>
            <p>And it was the great queſtion ſo much
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:115543:42"/>
agitated betwixt <hi>Job</hi> and his Friends, Whether thoſe dolefull changes that befell him were the cognizance of his inſincerity to God, and of Gods disfavour to him upon it, yea or no. His Friends taking ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage upon his preſent weakneſſe and diſtemper, maintain it ſtrongly againſt him in the affirmative, that they were: untill at length God himſelf ſteps in to the reſcue of the weaker ſide, and makes the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion (as all logicall <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Concluſio ſequitur de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biliorem partem.</hi> Keck. <hi>log. pag.</hi> 424.</note> concluſions do) to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the weaker part, determining it for <hi>Job</hi> againſt his Opponents in the negative, and telling them, that they ſpake not of <hi>Job,</hi> nor of his proceeding; towards him that which was right. <hi>Job</hi> laſt. verſ. 7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seneca</hi> a <hi>Stoick</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſpher hath a ſet <note place="margin">In libro de provid. cap. 4.</note> diſcourſe to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <hi>Cur bonts varis mala eveniant,</hi> why the evils of this life moſt commonly fall out to good men: and he concludes it thus, That temporall
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:115543:42"/>
evils are no ſign of Gods hatred to them. <note place="margin">Numquid tu inviſos eſſe <hi>Lacedemoniis</hi> ſuos liberos credis, quorum experiuntur indolem publice verberibus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motis? Non est hoc ſoevitia; certamen eſt.</note> For, doſt thou think (ſayes he) that the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> hated their Children, when as they experimented their diſpoſition to vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue by ſtripes in publick? No. So do we think Gods children in disfavour with him, becauſe he layes here ſore blows upon their bodies and eſtates by evil men, as his rods <note place="margin">So Tamerlain <hi>the</hi> Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian <hi>was call'd</hi> Fla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gellum Dei.</note> and ſcourges in it? No; for we ſee and feel many times (ſayes an experimentall patient of our own well) the deep lines and ſtrokes of Gods hand <note place="margin">Sir. I. M.</note> upon us, when as we cannot by our skill in Palmeſtry decipher his meaning in it, no more then the <hi>Malteſes</hi> could by the viper upon Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> hand judge of his condition to God-ward. <note place="margin">Acts 28. 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>For God ſometimes (that we may not thus judge) inverts humane order, and runs out his dealings towards us in the ordinary chanel of his univerſall provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:115543:43"/>
juſtice and equity, by which he wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters here all alike.</p>
            <p>Indeed they may ſeem (I grant) to go counter to our apprehended rules of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon right: yet are they alwaies agreeing both with Gods ſecret and revealed will, though (like the ſunne in its ſphear) not perceptible to us, becauſe too myſterious and dazzling: however many pretend to interpret them by a blaze of fire lighted at the naturall pride of their own private ſpirits, and that dimme twilight of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge which is in them; whenas they are altogether in the dark to the true light of Gods word and works herein.</p>
            <p>And here take in the opinion alſo of <hi>Epictetus</hi> another <hi>Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ick</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pia</hi> Epicteti <hi>ſententia, Non eſſe omnes Deo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſos, qui aerumnarum varietate luctantur, ſed eſſe arcanas cauſas, ad quas paucoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> potest per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venire curioſitas.</hi> Aul. G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll. <hi>noct. Att. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 18.</note> and Heathen man, which ſpeaks moſt Chriſtianly to this point, namely, That all are not hated of God, who do wraſtle here with variety of Miſeries: but that there are with God good
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:115543:43"/>
cauſes of it, though ſo ſecret that few can reach them.</p>
            <p>And therefore, albeit we cannot ſee how theſe actings of God may ſtand with his tender love to his children, and ſo may conceive an ill opinion of them; yet when we ſhall think ſeriouſly, that Gods thoughts and wayes are not as ours, it will teach <note place="margin">Iſa. 55. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> us to give them a more favourable inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation.</p>
            <p>For how dare hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane raſhneſſe (ſayes <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quomodo humana teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas audet reprehendere quod comprehendere non poteſt! De</hi> Conſid. <hi>l.</hi> 2.</note> Saint <hi>Bernard)</hi> repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend that which it cannot comprehend; in giving demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive reaſon why world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proſperity ſhould <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Noverca virtutis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitas,</hi> P. Chryſol <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de curial. nugis.</hi>
               </note> be virtues ſtepdame, and not her naturall mother!</p>
            <p>But (to cloſe up this diſcourſe) you ſee here by what hath been ſaid, that it is a great errour (howbeit now grown more then popular) to judge of perſons and cauſes by the events, whenas <hi>all</hi> outward
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:115543:44"/>
               <hi>things</hi> (ſayes <hi>Solomon) fall alike to all, neither can any judge of love or hatred by</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſt. c. 9. ver. 1.</note> 
               <hi>what is before him;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">See alſo <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 45. <hi>He makes his ſun riſe on the evil and on the good,</hi> &amp;c.</note> Proſperity and Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity being but ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble accidents to them, and no eſſentiall properties of them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are grounded upon worldly things that have ſo looſe and mouldring a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, as that a man cannot tell con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them what a day may bring forth. Again</p>
            <p>2. As worldly proſperity ſwels us up with a high opinion of our own Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe above others, ſo likewiſe of our own Greatneſſe. And this makes us ſlight thoſe that are under us, and deal hardly with them, (as to temporall things,) which we would not do, if we once conſider'd the mutability of it.</p>
            <p>And therefore if at any time God ſhall give up unto us thoſe we conceit our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, to be dealt with (if we will) by all harſhneſſe and extremity; yet are not we then to trample upon them in the pride
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:115543:44"/>
of our hearts, nor to adde more load to that which God hath already laid upon them, but rather to take off from it what <note place="margin">
                  <hi>As the virtue of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity is fortitude: ſo is temperance and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of proſperity. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r</hi> Francis Bacon, <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay</hi> 5.</note> we can, and to uſe them with all gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and compaſſion, with all mildneſſe and moderation, as conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering our ſelves, that we are not here to live alwayes as Gods upon earth, the ſame yeſterday, to day and for ever: but what is the bitter cup of their portion to day, may be ours to morrow.</p>
            <p>It ſpeaks out but a courſe and ignoble ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to crow and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Faciles motus mens ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſa capit.</hi> Ovid. <hi>Trict. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>eleg.</hi> 5.</note> over thoſe that are down. The very Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then thought it ſo, who had only the glimmering of nature to guide them; much more ought we Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, whom the Apoſtle exhorts, that our <hi>moderation may be known to all men.</hi> That as the Apoſtle will have his <hi>Corinthians</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Philipp. 4. 5.</note> to <hi>uſe the world with a</hi> tanquam, <hi>as if they uſed it not;</hi> ſo muſt they among us, that <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 31.</note>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:115543:45"/>
have wealth, power and authority, to uſe them, as if they uſed them not: that ſo when they ſhall fail us, (as they will ere long, ſince the wind <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The wind goeth towards the South, and turneth about unto the North; it whirleth about con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, and the wind returnes again (ſayes the</hi> Preacher) <hi>accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his circuits.</hi> Eccleſiaſtes 1. 6.</note> blows not alwayes out of one and the ſame favourable quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) we may then be able to ſay with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, That we never miſsimployed thoſe ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents of Gods outward favour to us unto the preſſure and deſtruction of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, but only to their relief and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.</p>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>David,</hi> in his tenth <hi>Pſalm,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 4. 5. and 6.</note> ſpeaks of ſome, who <hi>through the pride of their countenance do not ſeek after God, neither is God in all their thoughts.</hi> But <hi>their wayes are alwayes grievous; they puffe at their enemies, and ſay in their hearts, they ſhall never be moved, nor be in Adverſity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſuch were the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> who (beſides their barbarous cruelty to the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:115543:45"/>
under capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity) added this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all, that they <note place="margin">The School-men ſay <hi>Irriſio</hi> is <hi>mortale pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> in the Agent: Sure I a, it is <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tale ſupplicium</hi> in the Patient; for <hi>Ego illam anum irridere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e it ſinam?</hi> (ſayes he in the comedy;) <hi>ſatius eſt mihi quovis exitio in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terire.</hi> Terent. <hi>in</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria.</note> ſcoff'd and jeer'd at them in their miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, with <hi>Sing us now one of the ſongs</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 137. 3.</note> 
               <hi>of</hi> Sion. So alſo were the <hi>Edomites</hi> verſ. 7. who cryed over <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> in the day of her viſitation, <hi>Raſe it, raſe it even to the foundations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And were we ſure that the ſun of our earthly Happineſſe would alwayes ſtand ſtill in this our <hi>Gibeon,</hi> it may be we might take liberty to do the like, and think we did well in it too. But when as we come to conſider ſeriouſly, that there is no Solſtice here upon earth, but ſo ſoon as the Sun is come to his furtheſt Summer-point in our Horizon, it is then preſently verticall, and turning again to make Winter-weather with us, how will this aſſwage that ſwelling of pride that is within us, and make us humble?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:115543:46"/>
To this purpoſe there is a memorable hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Caganus</hi> King <note place="margin">Bucholc. <hi>Chron<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. pag.</hi> 669.</note> of the <hi>Huns,</hi> unto whom <hi>Theodorus Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicus</hi> being ſent in anembaſſy from <hi>Mauri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> the Emperour, to divert thoſe ſwarms of people where with <hi>Caganus</hi> at that time threatned to ſtorm the Empire, he apply'd himſelf to him in theſe words; <hi>Audi,</hi> Caga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Herodot. <hi>hist.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>utilem narratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem</hi> Seſoſtris, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Hear, ſayes he to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganus,</hi> a profitable narrative of <hi>Seſoſtris</hi> King of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> who being lifted up too high with his great Succeſſes againſt his enemies, cauſ'd four Kings taken priſoners to draw his triumphall Chariot, wherein one of them look'd back with ſmiles to the wheel of the Chariot, and being demanded his reaſon for it, anſwered; <q>That he ſmiled to ſee the ſpeak of the wheel now at the top, to be preſently at the bottome; and again that which is now at the bottome, to be and by at the top.</q> The very hearing whereof did ſo mollifie, and keep down the haughty princes ſpirit, that
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:115543:46"/>
it drew him a little to forbear his acts of hoſtility againſt the Emperour.</p>
            <p>And from this to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pick alſo of volubility, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem hiſtor. lib.</hi> 1.</note> did <hi>Croeſus</hi> draw an argument to diſſwade <hi>Cyrus</hi> from his intended inrode into <hi>Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thia,</hi> For if thou didſt lead (ſayes he) an immortall army, then is there no need for thee to ask my advice in it; but if thou doſt acknowledge thy ſelf a man, and a leader of mortals, then think that there is a wheel of humane affairs that turns about continually, and ſuffers nothing here below to ſtand long upon the ſame bottom.</p>
            <p>But this advice of <hi>Croeſus</hi> took no place with <hi>Cyrus:</hi> If it had, he would have kept himſelf (as the <hi>Tortoiſe</hi> doth) <hi>intra teſtudinem,</hi> within his own ſhell, within his own dominions, and not have cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſely uſurp'd upon the rightfull poſſeſſions of others to his own deſtruction; for ſee the iſſue and event of it.</p>
            <p>Even that God who is infinite in his Wiſdome, and terrible in his Power and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:115543:47"/>
He that reſiſts the proud, and looks <note place="margin">Pſal. 138. 6.</note> upon them afarre off; He (I ſay) made the pride of <hi>Cyrus</hi> ſerve <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Alios in cladem meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam praecipitavit indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne aucta falicitas.</hi> Boet. <hi>de Conſol. philos. l. 4. proſ.</hi> 6.</note> as a ſnare to take him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in, and to work his ruine: for he was no ſooner entred <hi>Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thia,</hi> but he found by ſad experience how unconſtant the world was, not looking now upon him with that ſmiling aſpect it did before; but the wind was now in another quarter, and (as the Wiſe man ſayes of <note place="margin">Prov. 23. 5.</note> Riches, that <hi>they make themſelves wings and fly away,)</hi> ſo did his former proſperity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take her ſelf now to her wings, and flew a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, his whole army <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conſule</hi> Juſtin, <hi>hiſt. lib.</hi> 1.</note> being quite defeated, and himſelf ſlain by <hi>Tomyris</hi> Queen of <hi>Scythia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A good example to make the ſecure wretch look about him, and to pull down the high looks of the proud.</p>
            <p>And therefore when ever any fluſhing of pride begins to riſe within thee, and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:115543:47"/>
to bud forth, as it is in <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> into vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, <note place="margin">Ezek. 7. 10.</note> and oppreſſion of others, then think thou heareſt ſome Monitor calling unto thee, as King <hi>Philip's</hi> Page did to him, <hi>Memento te eſſe mortalem,</hi> remember that <note place="margin">Q. Cur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> thou art mortall: ſo, remember that thou art changeable as well as others, and this will be an excellent means to keep it in.</p>
            <p>For tell me, would <hi>Cyrus,</hi> think you, have invaded <hi>Scythia,</hi> had he thought ſo ſad a fate would have attended him in it?</p>
            <p>Or would <hi>Pharaoh</hi> have oppreſs'd the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> ſo much, had he thought that God would have tumbled him up and down ſo <note place="margin">Exod. 5. chap.</note> much as he did, from one plague to another, and at laſt made the ſea his champion to revenge their injuries upon him?</p>
            <p>Or would <hi>Joſeph's</hi> brethren have perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted him as they did, if they had thought he ſhould afterwards have been lord over them?</p>
            <p>Or the <hi>Gileadites</hi> have expelled <hi>Jephtha,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Judg. chap. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> had they known he would have been ſuch a ſhelter againſt a ſtorm, and of ſuch uſe unto them againſt the <hi>Ammonites?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or (to ſay no more) would <hi>Darius</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:115543:48"/>
have call'd <hi>Alexander Philip</hi>'s boy in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſion <note place="margin">Q. Cutt.</note> of him, had he known that he ſhould have been conquered by him?</p>
            <p>No; Little do proud men think that the water which is now in the float, will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently be in the ebbe; and that the ſpoak of the wheel which is now at the top, may quickly be at the bottome: and then he that is the greateſt now among us, may come (how ſoon he knows not) to ſtand in need of the meaneſt creature whom he now deſpiſes.</p>
            <p>It is wiſdome then for every Chriſtian, whenas he is at the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sapienter omnes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rahant v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nto nimium ſecundo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urgida vela,</hi> Hor. <hi>carm. l. 2. od. 10.</hi>
               </note> top of the wheel, and may lord it over thoſe that are beneath, yet not to overlook them with a ſcornfull eye, but to let down his ſpirit, and (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle exhorts us) to condeſcend to men of <note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. 15.</note> low degree: For one ſcale is not alwayes in depreſſion. No; This were <hi>dura infaelicit as, a</hi> very hard and high meaſure of infelicity. Neither is the other alwayes in elevation: This were <hi>foellcit as miſeranda,</hi> a happineſſe
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:115543:48"/>
to be pitied. But the alternate wave of the beam keeps them both in aw, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the proud perſon, who ſeems unto me as a bird tied to a ſtring, which if it fly too high, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and draws in the ſtring and puls it down again. And ſo if we ſhall let out our ſpirits too high with pride, God hath then a line of viciſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in his hand to pull us in at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>David</hi> ſaid in his proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <note place="margin">Pſal. 30. 6.</note> that he ſhould never be moved, his mountain was made ſo ſtrong; yet God did but hide his face from him a little, and he was troubled.</p>
            <p>Naturally then we are too apt to know <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Res ſecundoe non habent unquam modum.</hi> Sen. <hi>in</hi> OEdip.</note> no meaſure in a high fortune; but (as a perſon of Honour and <note place="margin">The Lord C. in his 74 meditat.</note> Piety in this nation ſaid) Although in the heat of ſummer we eaſily believe there will come after it a cold ſeaſon of froſt and ſnow: yet are we ſo ſtupid as in Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity not to conſider of Adverſity, though
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:115543:49"/>
the one be as ſucceſſive as the other. And this makes us to exalt our ſelves ſo much above all that is called God. That as it is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable touching the book of <hi>Eſther</hi> (which is nothing elſe but a Declaration of acts done in reference to the Greatneſſe, Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Glory of <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> the <hi>Perſian</hi> Monarch, as to the principall inſtrument of them) that in that whole book the name of God is not ſo much as mentioned at all: So doth it alſo commonly fall out, that while we are here in the ruffe of our worldly Glory and Proſperity, we ſeldome or never ſpeak of God, and as ſeldome think of him, but ſet our ſelves up in his room, as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> did, who ſpake too big, and too much of himſelf, ſaying, <hi>Is not this great Babel that I have built for the houſe of my Kingdome, by the might of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dan. 4. 30.</note> 
               <hi>my power, and for the honour of my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty?</hi> As the fly ſaid in the Apologue when it was got up to the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quam magnam vim pulveris excitavi!</hi> Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſop. <hi>fab. pag. 62.</hi>
               </note> top of the wheel, See what a duſt I make! So, ſee what a duſt
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:115543:49"/>
makes this poor Worm, what a <hi>Mying</hi> there is with him in the height of his pride! nothing but <hi>my</hi> Kingdome, <hi>my</hi> Power, and <hi>my</hi> Majeſty: but as for God, <hi>Ne gry qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem,</hi> There is not a <note place="margin">Eraſm. Adag. <hi>pag.</hi> 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.</note> word of him; He is not in all his thoughts.</p>
            <p>And therefore how ſoon the houſe of his Kingdome fell upon his head, yea how ſhort-liv'd the might of his power was, and the honour of his majeſty, you may ſee by the next verſe, where it is ſaid, That while the word was in the Kings mouth, there fell a voice from heaven ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>O</hi> Nebuchadnezzar, <hi>to thee be it ſpoken, Thy Kingdome is departed from thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The world then may well be compared to the ſea of glaſſe which Saint <hi>John</hi> ſaw in his viſion, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velat.</hi> 4. 6. and there be alſo, that from the <note place="margin">Leo <hi>his Conc. funeb. in obit. Doctoris</hi> Featlael.</note> reſemblance of the one to the other, interpret it thus. For</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:115543:50"/>
Firſt, It reſembles the ſea either for its ebbing and flowing: or elſe for the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain change of it: for how ſoon is the face of the ſea alter'd? In <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nune strato oequore blanditur mare: nunc ſluctibus inhorreſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Boet. <hi>de Conſolat. Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſph. lib. 2. proſ. 2.</hi>
               </note> one and the ſame hour (it may be) thou mayeſt ſee her ſmiling upon thy veſſel, and frowning too; playing with it, and ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing it up. <hi>Noli igitur</hi> (ſayes the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſt) <hi>tranquillitati e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Sen, <hi>de tranquill. ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi. Eodem die quo libi luſerant navigia, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>entur,</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>credere. i. e.</hi> Do not therefore truſt too much to her ſmooth and calm looks; <hi>in hoc enim momento ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> evertitur,</hi> for in one moment doth ſhe appear wrinkled with billowes, and turns about from a calm unto a ſtorm.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles alſo glaſſe, and <note place="margin">We ſay therefore of glaſs uſually, that it ſtands in harms way; and ſome melancholy perſons have conceited their bodies to be of a glaſſy ſubſtance, and would not let any man touch them for fear of breaking. See <hi>Burton's</hi> Melancholy.</note> that either for its brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſſe, becauſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is ſooner bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: or elſe for its
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:115543:50"/>
ſlipperineſſe, becauſe he that walks upon glaſſe can have no ſure footing; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for any man to preſume upon the ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe of it muſt needs be very dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous.</p>
            <p>That as the ancient <hi>Romans</hi> uſed to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh their dayes into <note place="margin">Godwin <hi>Rom. Antiq. lib. 2. §. 3. cap. 1. &amp;</hi> Etaſm. <hi>Adag. pag.</hi> 105.</note> 
               <hi>Dies albi</hi> and <hi>Dies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tri,</hi> white and black dayes: ſo doth God, and there is no man but hath the later of theſe as well as the former, his black as well as his white dayes.</p>
            <p>Oh the madneſſe then of wicked men, who are alwayes plotting againſt the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and gnaſhing upon them with their teeth! <hi>At ridebit Deus,</hi> ſayes <hi>David, But</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 37. 12.</note> 
               <hi>God ſhall laugh at them</hi> for it: and he gives this reaſon verſ. 13. <hi>becauſe he ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es that their day is coming. i. e.</hi> he ſees clearly that their black and diſmall day is coming upon them, though themſelves will
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:115543:51"/>
not ſee it through the pride and ſecurity of their ſpirits; yea, and he knows alſo punctually when it will be: though we know it not, for though to day may be fair and ſhining, yet may to morrow be dark and tempeſtuous with them; Since we know not what a day may bring forth.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all (becauſe I am loth that my ſun ſhould ſet in a cloud;) The conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Uſe</hi> 3.</note> of this point may ſerve as a good an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidote againſt deſpair <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nemo deſperet meliora lapſus—probibet</hi> Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho <hi>ſtare fortunam,</hi> Sen. Thyeſt. <hi>trag.</hi> 2.</note> in an afflicted condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; or as a cordiall to ſtay up our ſpirits in the ſaddeſt and moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed times, and to teach us patience and contentedneſſe in them: that ſo as in proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity we ſhould not ſay, we ſhall never be moved, ſo neither in adverſity, that we ſhall never be deliver'd; when we ſhall conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that what weight of affliction ſoever <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Non ſi male nunc, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lim ſic erit.</hi> Horat. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>ode</hi> 10.</note> we ly under, is not of a continuant, but of a changeable nature. And to this end
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:115543:51"/>
we have the ſure ſtaff of Gods promiſe unto his children to lean upon, as in the tenth chapter to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> where he ſayes thus, <hi>Yet a little while,</hi> or rather as it runs in the <hi>Greek,</hi> yet <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 37.</note> how very very little while, (with a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diminutive) <hi>and he that ſhall come, will come, and will not tarry.</hi> And in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent verſe he tells them, they have need of patience, that they may receive this promiſe. And in the twelfth chapter to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> the Apoſtle takes up an exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to it from the Wiſe man, and <note place="margin">Prov. 3. 11.</note> makes a conſolatory uſe of it to his <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews,</hi> withall taking them to taske for their forgetfulneſſe of it; <hi>And ye have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten the exhortation which ſpeaks unto</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 5.</note> 
               <hi>you, as unto children: My ſonne, deſpiſe not thou the chaſtening of the Lord, nor faint,</hi> or be not broken in mind, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ne animo frangitor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſic</hi> B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> (as others tranſlate it) <hi>when thou art rebuked of him.</hi> For <hi>we had</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of our fleſh, who verily chaſtened us
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:115543:52"/>
a few dayes after their own pleaſure,</hi> and <hi>we</hi> were patient under their rod, and <hi>gave</hi> 
               <note place="margin">See the 9. and 10. ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note> 
               <hi>them reverence, but God</hi> a few dayes only, <hi>for our profit. Shall we not then be much rather in ſubjection to him who is the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ſpirits, and live?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus when <hi>Boetius,</hi> that Chriſtian Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul and Martyr at <hi>Rome,</hi> was wrongfully deprived by <hi>Theodoricus</hi> of his Honours, Eſtate and Liberty, Philoſophy brings in what we call Gods providence, comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him in theſe words;</p>
            <p>I turn about my wheel continually, and delight to tumble things <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rotam meam volubili orbe ſemper verſo, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſummiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que infima mutare gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens. Quid igitur a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimo contabeſcis,</hi> &amp;c. Boet. <hi>de Conſol. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Proſ.</hi> 2.</note> upſide down: why then doth thy heart ſhrink within thee, when as this changeableneſſe of mine is cauſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for thee to hope for better things?</p>
            <p>And ſo alſo, when many of our brethren were heretofore in exile for their Religion in Queen <hi>Marie's</hi> dayes, what (I pray)
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:115543:52"/>
did that <hi>Jewell</hi> of our Church comfort them <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> Juelli vits.</note> with, but only this, <hi>Haec non durabunt, aetatem</hi> Theſe will not endure an Age? as indeed you know they did not, her reign being not full out ſix years time.</p>
            <p>And with the ſame conſideration alſo ſhould we cheare up our ſelves now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that black cloud that hangs over the Church, that it will <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Non ſemper imbres nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bibus biſpid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s manane in agros.</hi> Hor. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>ode</hi> 9.</note> not endure an Age, but be as <hi>Ephraim's</hi> righteouſneſſe was, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <note place="margin">Hoſ. 6. 4.</note> like the morning cloud, or as the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dew that paſſes away.</p>
            <p>To this end, it will not be amiſſe to note, how the afflictions of Gods people in the Scripture, are run out not by any long tract of time, as by an Age, Year, Moneth, Week or the like; but by the ſhorteſt meaſures that can be, as by a Day: now a Day (you know) holds not long, but is quickly gone, even as a flying bird, or a poaſt that runneth by. And this good
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:115543:53"/>
               <hi>Hezekiah</hi> calls the time of <hi>Sennacheribs</hi> rage againſt <hi>Judah,</hi> a Day of trouble, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 37. <hi>verſ.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>Or if this be not enough, you have them then contracted within a leſſer room, and meaſur'd only by a Night, which is no more but the dark ſide of a naturall day, and therefore is a great deal ſhorter. And this made the Prophet <hi>David</hi> ſay, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30. verſ. 5. That <hi>heav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neſſe may endure for a night, but joy cometh in the morning.</hi> The time then that heavineſſe ſhall endure to the Godly can be but a Night at the longeſt, but whether it ſhall be ſo long or no, the Prophet is very uncertain and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied, for which cauſe he expreſſes it here with a <hi>May be, Heavineſſe may endure for a night.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if this expreſſion be not full enough to ſet forth the brevity of them, our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> doth it then by an Hour, which is ſhorter yet, and but the four and twentieth part of a naturall Day; for ſo he calls the time of his perſecution by the High Prieſts and Elders of the people, Their <hi>hour,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:115543:53"/>
and the power of Darkneſſe. Luk.</hi> 22. 53.</p>
            <p>Or, if this be yet too long a ſpace to ſet forth the brevity of their afflictions, and to give a through Comfort to Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, their little continuance is then expreſs'd by a Moment, which I am ſure is ſhort enough; ſo you have it <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54. verſ. 7. <hi>For a ſmall moment</hi> (ſayes God to his Church) <hi>have I forſaken thee, but with great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy will I gather thee:</hi> And again verſ. 8. <hi>In a little wrath I hid my face from thee for a moment, but with everlaſting kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe will I have mercy upon thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or laſt of all, if any time can be ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then this, it muſt then be the preſent time; yet ſuch are the ſufferings of Gods children, in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> account, but <hi>the Sufferings of the preſent time,</hi> Rom. 8. 18. and a ſhorter time then this there cannot be. For as the <hi>French</hi> our <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Howell</hi> in the life of <hi>Lewis</hi> the thirteenth.</note> neighbours are ſaid to be for their inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derateneſſe, <hi>Animalia ſine praeterito &amp; futu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro,</hi> Creatures that have reſpect neither to time paſt nor time to come: ſo may we ſay
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:115543:54"/>
of the preſent time, That it is as ſhort a meaſure as can poſſibly be imagined, having in it nothing either of time paſt or future, the firſt of the two being dead already, and the later of them being not yet born unto us. And yet we ſee here for all this that Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> when he had caſt up the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of all which he ſuffered in the cauſe of Chriſt, how he reckons and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes it to be only the ſuffering of the preſent time, and not worthy to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the glory that ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He that obſerves the wind</hi> (ſayes <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon) ſhall never ſow, and he that obſerves</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſt. c. 11. v. 4.</note> 
               <hi>the clouds ſhall never reap.</hi> Such are our Troubles, ſuch our Afflictions, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they blow ſtrong againſt us, yet like ſome high and mighty wind, they will not hold; yea though they fall upon us as thick as hail, yet are they not ſo fix'd for ever, but a change ſhall come. which ſhould make us in any temptation to deſpair and diſtruſt of Gods providence, check and chide our ſpirits, as the prophet <hi>David</hi> did his with that objurgation, (which
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:115543:54"/>
for the remarkableneſſe of it is thrice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, in the two and fourtieth and three and fourtieth Pſalms;) <hi>Why art thou caſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 42. verſ. 5. and 11. Again Pſal. 43. laſt verſe.</note> 
               <hi>down, O my ſoul? and why art thou diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted within me? Still hope in God; for I ſhall yet praiſe him, who is the health of my countenance and my God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scaliger</hi> tells us of one <hi>Palavicine</hi> an <hi>Italian,</hi> and kinſman of his, that had in one <note place="margin">In lib. 18. ſubtil.</note> night his hair metamorphoſed from black to white: And I apply it thus, That al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though now Gods people may <hi>ly,</hi> as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did, <hi>among the pots,</hi> (to uſe the Prophets words,) and be like ſome Scullion <note place="margin">Pſal. 68. verſ. 13.</note> fullied and black'd with the burning coals of Affliction; yet may one day of Gods favour to us work a great alteration with us, and put ſuch a candy of Proſperity upon us, as that we ſhall be, as it is there verſ. 14. even <hi>as white as the ſnow in</hi> Salmon.</p>
            <p>And therefore, as <hi>Jobs</hi> reſolution was, <hi>to wait all the dayes of his appointed time,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Job 14. ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ. 14.</note> 
               <hi>untill his change ſhould come;</hi> ſo ſhould every good man wait upon God all the dayes that he ſhall be pleaſed to lay trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:115543:55"/>
upon him, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther immediately by <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Accepimus peritura perituri: quid queri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur? Ad hoc institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti ſumus.</hi> Sen. <hi>lib. de provid. c.</hi> 6.</note> himſelf, or elſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately by the hands of evil men as his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments in it; as knowing that it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed but for a little while, at the moſt but a <hi>biduum</hi> or a <hi>triduum,</hi> and then a change ſhall come, and bring him delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For in mount</hi> Sion <hi>and in</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>there ſhall be deliverance, as the Lord hath</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joel 2. 32.</note> 
               <hi>ſaid: neither ſhall the rod of the ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly alwayes lye upon the back of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 125. 3.</note> but <hi>after two dayes he will revive us, and the third day we ſhall live in his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 6. 2.</note> 
               <hi>ſight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherefore ſeeing we are compaſs'd about,</hi> (as the Authour to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> ſpeaks) <hi>with ſuch a cloud of witneſſes, let us run</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 1. 2. and 3.</note> 
               <hi>on with patience the race that is ſet before us, looking unto</hi> Jeſus <hi>the beginner and finiſher of our faith, who for the joy that was ſet before him, endured the croſſe and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſhame. Yea let us conſider him that
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:115543:55"/>
endured ſuch contradictions of ſinners, that ſo we may not be faint and weary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now <hi>Comfort</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>(ſaith my</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 40. 1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>God)</hi> yea comfort her at the very heart, <hi>and tell her that her ſinnes are pardoned, and her warfare is accompliſhed.</hi> For <hi>the Lord knows,</hi> ſayes Saint <hi>Peter, how to deliver the godly out of temptation,</hi> and to <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 9.</note> make a way for them to eſcape: That <hi>as the ſufferings of Chriſt in them do abound,</hi> ſo hath God many wayes to make <hi>their</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 1. 5.</note> 
               <hi>conſolations abound</hi> alſo. If the Devil and his Engineers have <hi>Mille nocendi artes,</hi> a thouſand wayes to hurt and deſtroy them, God will either find or make as many wayes to preſerve them: whereof ſome he will have to be more ſecret and under ground, others again more open and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious to the eyes of the world; as either by reſtraining the fury and malice of their perſecutours, and ſtopping their mouthes, that they ſhall not hurt them, as he did the mouthes of the Lions from hurting <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel;</hi> or elſe by taking them off by his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying hand of judgement in the full car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reer of their pride, as he did <hi>Pharaoh, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:115543:56"/>
Herod, Agrippa, Julian</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and many ſuch like; or if none of theſe wayes, yet by ingratiating them, and giving them favour in the ſight of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, as he did the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the eyes of the <hi>Aegyptians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as God knows <hi>how</hi> to deliver the godly, ſo alſo <hi>when</hi> to do it; and a great deal ſooner it may be then they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, even within the ſpace and turning about of one day: Since none of us know what a day may bring forth.</p>
            <closer>Trin uni Deo Gloria.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:115543:56"/>
            <head>Aſpiratio.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lmighty God, who ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt the <hi>Sea</hi> of this World by thy power, &amp; whoſe paths are in the rougheſt <hi>waters;</hi> We the unworthieſt of all thy ſervants commit our frail <hi>Barks,</hi> with all that we have to the <hi>ſteerage</hi> of thee our great <hi>Pilot,</hi> &amp; faithfull Preſerver: beſeeching thee ſo to order by thy good hand of Providence all outward contingencies to us, that we may be able to <hi>beare up</hi> through them with a ſteady and even <hi>courſe,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſeverall <hi>storms</hi> we ſhall meet with in this <hi>paſſage</hi> to our bleſſed <hi>Harbour</hi> of Eternity. And however earthly things may like
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:115543:57"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:115543:57"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:115543:58"/>
               <hi>watery Billows</hi> be every day <hi>row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling up</hi> &amp; <hi>down</hi> in their viciſsitudes about us; yet ſuffer, oh ſuffer not the heavenly truth of our Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Religion to <hi>flote</hi> about any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſo uncertainly among us, nor our ſelves to be as children <hi>toſs'd</hi> to and fro with every <hi>wind</hi> of Doctrine. But let us be conſtant and unwavering in the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of that holy faith we have received; and (Thou that art the God of Truth) be graciouſly pleaſed to <hi>stay</hi> us <hi>up</hi> firmly in it by the ſacred Scriptures, which are thy word of Truth, and the ſole <hi>Anchor</hi> of our faith to reſt upon. Lord, <hi>pull in</hi> the <hi>ſailes</hi> of our deſires towards fleeting and tranſitory ſubſtances: for who will caſt his eyes upon that which
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:115543:58"/>
hath wings to flee away as an Eagle towards heaven. <hi>Bailaſt</hi> our ſpirits with Humility in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous condition; and when we have the higheſt and moſt pleaſing <hi>gale</hi> of the worlds fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour for us, give us to <hi>ſtrike</hi> our <hi>ſpreading ſailes</hi> of Pride, and to make our Lenity and Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be known to all men, for the Lord is nigh at hand. But if thou in thy juſt judgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us for our manifold and hainous ſins, ſhalt cauſe ſome <hi>croſs wind</hi> or other to <hi>blow</hi> upon us, and give us over to <hi>ſhipwrack</hi> in our temporalls; Supply then, we entreat thee, their want with thy ſpiritualls of Patience, Faith and other ſuffering graces; That although the <hi>tempest</hi> be never ſo
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:115543:59"/>
               <hi>boiſterous</hi> without, yet we may enjoy within a Chriſtian <hi>calmneſs</hi> of ſpirit, in a happy quietude and contentedneſs of mind with all thy dealings towards us, and not ſet down our reſts upon the creature, which is ſo reſtleſs with us, but amidſt the ſundry and various changes of the world, may there fix our hearts, where only true and unchangeable joys are to be found, through <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> our Lord.</p>
            <closer>Trin-uni Deo Gloria.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:115543:59"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
